<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians hope triumphing in these glorious truths; [brace] 1. That Christ the ground of hope, is God, and not meer man, against the Arians, and other unbelieving Christians. 2. That Christ is the true Messiah, against the unbelieving Jews. 3. That there is another life besides this, against the grosse atheist. 4. That the soul of man is immortall, and doth not sleep till the day of resurrection, against the errour of some seeming semi-atheists. 5. How the hope of heaven should be attained, whilst we are on earth, against the carnall worldlings. 6. How this hope may be discerned where it is, and attained where it is not, for the comfort of every poor Christian. All which truths are briefly pointed out and cleared, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable House of Lords in the Abby-Church at Westminster on Wednesday, May 28. being the day appointed for solemn and publike humiliation. / By Jeremiah Whitaker. Published by order of the House of Peers.</title>
            <author>Whittaker, Jeremiah, 1599-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E286_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860878</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860878</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96328)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E286[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians hope triumphing in these glorious truths; [brace] 1. That Christ the ground of hope, is God, and not meer man, against the Arians, and other unbelieving Christians. 2. That Christ is the true Messiah, against the unbelieving Jews. 3. That there is another life besides this, against the grosse atheist. 4. That the soul of man is immortall, and doth not sleep till the day of resurrection, against the errour of some seeming semi-atheists. 5. How the hope of heaven should be attained, whilst we are on earth, against the carnall worldlings. 6. How this hope may be discerned where it is, and attained where it is not, for the comfort of every poor Christian. All which truths are briefly pointed out and cleared, in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable House of Lords in the Abby-Church at Westminster on Wednesday, May 28. being the day appointed for solemn and publike humiliation. / By Jeremiah Whitaker. Published by order of the House of Peers.</title>
                  <author>Whittaker, Jeremiah, 1599-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Miller for John Bellamy at the sign of the three golden-Lions in Cornhill near the Royal-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print on leaf A1v.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st XV, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:113005:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Mercurij, May</hi> 28. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day ordered by the Lords in Parliament, that M. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> who preached this day before the Lords in Parliament, is hereby thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the great pains hee took in his Sermon, and is deſired by their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to print and publiſh the ſame, which is not to be printed or reprinted by any, but by authority under his own hand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Brown, Cler. Parliamentorum.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 15. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I appoint <hi>John Bellamy</hi> to print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jeremiah Whitaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113005:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE CHRISTIANS HOPE TRIVMPHING In theſe glorious Truths;</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> That Chriſt the ground of hope, is God, and not meer man, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Arians, and other unbelieving Chriſtians.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> That Chriſt is the true Meſsiah, againſt the unbelieving Jews.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> That there is another life beſides this, againſt the groſſe Atheiſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> That the ſoul of man is immortall, and doth not ſleep till the day of Reſurrection, against the errour of ſome ſeeming ſemi-Atheiſts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5.</hi> How the hope of Heaven ſhould be attained, whilst we are on earth, against the carnall worldlings.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6.</hi> How this hope may be diſcerned where it is, and attained where it is not, for the comfort of every poor Chriſtian.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All which Truths are brieſly pointed out and cleared, In a Sermon preached before the Right Honourable Houſe of LORDS in the Abby-Church at</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>on Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, May 28. being the day appointed for ſolemn and publike Humiliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Jeremiah Whitaker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe of Peers,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> G. Miller <hi>for</hi> John Bellamy <hi>at the Sign of the three gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-Lions in Cornhill near the Royall-Exchange, 1645.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113005:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113005:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE The HOUSE of PEERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Theiſme is the great ſin of the world, dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall among the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and practicall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> who profeſse <hi>they know</hi> God, and yet <hi>in works deny him.</hi> Satan cares not much what is our profeſsion, ſo be may rule in our converſation; he knows where opinions have not ſtrength to better practice; there ill fractice, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,<note place="margin">Quid prodeſſe nebis praerog a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riva Chriſtiani nominis poteſt, quod nos fideles eſſe jactamus, quod <hi>Gothos</hi> ac <hi>Uvandalos</hi> hareticos deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus, cum ipſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eretica pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur? <hi>Salv.</hi> de Gub. l <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> will weaken the beſt opinions; and what <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage is it for us</hi> to have the face of Chriſtians, and the hearts and heads of <hi>Pagans?</hi> that our rule is ſtraight, and our lives crooked?<note n="*" place="margin">Lex bona, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris eſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti: vita autem non bona, crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis noſtri. <hi>Salv</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> That God hath made our light clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, tis Gods free goodneſſe: that our lives are darker, tis our own vileneſse.</p>
            <p>It was his ſad complaint, that lived in ſuch dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dayes as theſe, when the <hi>Goths, Hunns</hi> and <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalls</hi> over ran the world, and all Chriſtendome put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a burning flame, that the lives of Chriſtians fell ſhort of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and did equall the worſt of the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:113005:3"/>It is no wonder, that when our unbeleife que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions the deity of Christ, the verity of Scriptures, the mortality of the ſoule, and ſo ſhakes the pillars of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that the Lord hath a ſtrong controverſy with the world, and cauſeth all the foundations of the earth to ſhake, and to be out of order.</p>
            <p>The way to cure the bleeding diſtempers of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is for all men to endeavour to get inward perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions anſwerable to their <hi>outward profeſſions;</hi> for as theſe main principles are more or leſſe beleeved; ſo is the heart and life of man better, or worſe ordered. When the ſoul is once fully perſwaded, that Chriſt is God, that he is the true Meſſiah, that there is another life beſides this, that the Lord Christ is ready to come to judgement, <hi>and his reward is with him;</hi> then the ſoul begins to ſeek and beg an interest in Chriſt, to flee from wrath to come, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the hopes of Heaven, whilſt we are on earth: and this hope, when once truly attained, carries the ſoul farre above the <hi>comforts of life,</hi> and beyond the <hi>fears of death,</hi> and makes men ſee no life to be ſo comfortable, as that life which is most ſerviceable.</p>
            <p>Your birth (Right Honourable) hath made you above <hi>other men,</hi> this hope will make you above <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and this communion with the great God will make daily additions to your greatneſse. Then are men <hi>high-born</hi> indeed, when they <hi>are born</hi> again of the moſt <hi>high God:</hi> and then are the ſons of Nobles truly great, when there
<pb facs="tcp:113005:3"/>are added inward ſupernaturall principles of <hi>ſpirituall greatneſſe.</hi> Its the obſervation of one (<note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Epiſt. ad <hi>1.</hi> Cor. c. <hi>1.</hi> Hom <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> no mean man) That ſome naturally are of a high ſtature; others, that are low, have ſhoes and pantables, to heighten them to a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatneſſe; which of theſe will you call truly high or great? He that is ſo by an adventitiall ſeparable additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or he that is ſo by a growth thats naturall? It is one thing to be highly esteem'd of others, another to have a minde worthy of eſteem in it ſelf. One man thinks clay to be clay, and deſpiſeth it; another thinks clay to be gold, and admires it: which of theſe two is high? Is it not he that deſpiſeth a peece of earth? and who is vile and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but he that adores a peece of earth, and ſpends his ſoul to <hi>load himſelf with thick clay?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2.6.</note> that man who in the height of outward greatneſſe accounts himſelf but duſt and aſhes; his minde is full of inward excellency: he that admires and adores himſelf, will not look upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as gilded clay, is of an abject minde, and much delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the midſt of all outward eminency: to have high thoughts of things moſt mean, and mean thoughts of things moſt high, infallibly argues the minde to be full of weakneſse, others ſay, to be <hi>full of baſeneſſe.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chryſ. ibid.</note> He ſpake like a Noble man indeed, that ſaid, <hi>Let their honour and wealth periſh, that thinke all greatneſſe in the world like one daies communion with the great God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To clear up theſe great principles hath been the aime of
<pb facs="tcp:113005:4"/>theſe weak endeavours. Tis the arm of the mighty God that alone can rebuke the ſpirit of unbelief: therefore that the great God,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.27.</note> who perſwades <hi>Japhet</hi> to <hi>dwell in the tents of Shem</hi> may imprint theſe eternall characters up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your hearts, and lift you up <hi>to ſit in heavenly places with Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1 6. Luk. 10.20.</note> that your <hi>names may be written in heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.8.</note> and that you may for ever inherit the <hi>thrones of glory,</hi> is the earneſt prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble Servant in the Lord, Jeremiah Whitaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113005:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at a late Faſt, before the Right Honourable the Houſe of PEERS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 15.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If in this life only we have hope in Chriſt, we are of all men moſt miſerable.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable and Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD hath raiſed many of you up to be higher then your brethren, as <hi>Saul</hi> was higher then the people from the ſhoulders upward, and ſet you as Cedars in Lebanon, and Oaks in Baſhan, and cauſed the <hi>mountains to pour down fatneſſe upon you, and the hills rivers of oyl;</hi> and though you could not but come into the world as others, clothed with common humane frailty, yet the Lord hath laid a foundation of greatneſſe for you in the wombe, and prepared honours for you from the breſts: he hath placed you in <hi>Eden</hi> the garden of the Lord, and hath made <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very precious stone to become your covering, the Topaz, Diamond,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 28.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>Beryl, Onyx and the Jasper, and you are as the anointed Cherub that covereth:</hi> what ever God hath been to others, certainly he hath been no hard Maſter unto you, he hath cauſed you to be the head of the Families, that you might be the ſtay of the tribes thereof, that you might be the repairers of breaches, and the reſtorers of waſte places to dwel in. Now he that hath done theſe great things for you, expecteth great things from you. It is a certaine principle, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113005:5"/>in Scripture, but according to the light of nature, <hi>That to whom much is given,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>of them much is required,</hi> and though this be ſo equall that none can denie it, yet the heart of man is ſo corrupt, that few walke by the light of this principle, in making it their great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne to returne unto God <hi>according to the mercies which they have recelved from God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron 32.</note> I know tis difficult when God hath made any great in the eyes of others, not to be great in their owne eyes; and when the world bringeth them up into the bed of love, not to be overcome with thoſe embraces: where the danger is ſo great, vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancie ſhould be the greater, that it may never be ſaid of any of you, as of <hi>Tyre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezck. 28.17.</note> 
               <hi>Thy heart was lifted up becauſe of thine owne beautie, and thou haſt corrupted thy wiſedome, thine eyes have been daze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with looking upon thine owne brightneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver 18.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore I will caſt thee to the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 19.</note> 
               <hi>I will bring thee to aſhes on the earth: All that know thee amongst the people ſhall be astoniſhed at thee: and thou ſhalt be a terrour, and never ſhalt thou be any more.</hi> To prevent this ſinne and miſery, that ſo this eternall breach may never be upon you, and your families, I have read this <hi>Text</hi> as a ſoveraigne An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote, as a ſtrong preſervative againſt all this evill. If this one Conſideration might dwell on the hearts of great men, That all they have is from the great God, and all they have in hand is nothing to that they may have in hope; and that the greateſt eſtate in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is nothing to that which may be in reverſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and that all the good things they enjoy, (if ten thouſand times more) are not able to make them happy;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6.6 9.8.</note> and that if a man could <hi>live a thouſand years twice told,</hi> and rejoyce in them all, yet all that cometh is but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that at the end of this life there muſt be an end of all theſe comforts, and all this brightneſſe muſt goe under a dark cloud; Surely then no wiſe man but in this life would provide for a better; and not onely make it his deſigne, but his delight to lay up for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a good foundation againſt the time to come, and ſo for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment uſe theſe temporalls, that he might for ever enjoy eternals: he that hath once got ſight of Heaven, taſted effectually the powers of the world to come, ſeen the vanitie and emptineſſe of all condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions here below, conſidered what it is to enjoy God to all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would not for all the world have his portion in this life, but would ſay with the Apoſtle, If in this life onely we had hope, we were of all men the moſt miſerable.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113005:5"/>
            <p>The ſcope of the Apoſtle in this Chapter is, to prove the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the dead, againſt that wicked opinion of the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jewes, Who ſaid there were no reſurrection, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, nor Spirit, Act.</hi> 23.8. and againſt the erroneous aſſertion of ſome ſeduced Chriſtians, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus, who as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth erred,</hi> confeſſing a reſurrection, but ſaying <hi>it was paſſed already, and ſo over threw the faith of ſome:</hi> which opinion began, like an ulcerous Canker, to ſpread it ſelfe in the mindes of many, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.18. The Apoſtle that he might ſtrangle theſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the birth, proveth that there <hi>ſhall</hi> be a reſurrection, by many unanſwerable Arguments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the reſurrection of Chriſt, If Chriſt the head be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen up above the waters, then the members united to the head can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not periſh—ver. 12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, From the many abſurdities that will follow, <hi>viz.</hi> That all that are aſleep are periſhed, <hi>ver.</hi> 18, 19. and that then there ſhould be more venom in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> to induce deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then vertue in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> to produce reſtauration, <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21, 22.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He proveth it from the perfection of Chriſts kingdome, He muſt reigne till he have put all under his feet. The laſt enemie that ſhall be ſubdued, is death, <hi>ver,</hi> 25, 26.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, From the practice of Chriſtians, who in baptiſing, profeſſed willingnes to die for Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, From the great ſufferings of the Apoſtle in this life, in <hi>jeopardie every haur, dying daily, fighting with beaste at Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, ver.</hi> 30, 31, 32.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, From the abſurd practice of the Epicures of thoſe times, which the light of nature cannot but condemne, who drown'd their ſoules in their bodies, and their bodies in luſts, who would have no time <hi>to live</hi> longer then they have time <hi>to ſinne,</hi> and when there is an end of <hi>ſinning,</hi> wiſh there might be an end <hi>of being,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Let us eate and drinks, for to morrow we ſhall die, ver.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>Amongſt theſe Arguments the words of my Text are one, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, there muſt be a reſurrection from the dead: otherwiſe the worſt men ſhould be the moſt happy, and the beſt men the moſt miſerable: which is ſo abſurd, againſt, not onely the light of Scripture, but the light of nature, that the very naming of it is reputed by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113005:6"/>the Apoſtle a ſufficient confutation of it, for if we had hopes one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are foure parts conſiderable in the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the foundation of all the comfort we doe enjoy, or can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a Chriſtians reſting upon this foundation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Extent of this hope, not onely in this life, but in the life to come.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the reaſon of that Extent, for if this hope did not looke beyond the grave and judgement to Eternity, then of all men the beſt men were the moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>From theſe foure parts there ariſe foure Obſervations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Lord Jeſus, the foundation of all the comforts we enjoy, or can expect, is <hi>the Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that thoſe that looke on him as Chriſt, and would have benefit by him, muſt be united to him, they muſt be taken off from themſelves and the creature, and ſettle their <hi>hopes on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, thoſe that would have their hopes in Chriſt, muſt be fully perſwaded, that there is another life beſides this life; and that it is their duty in this life to get the hope of a better.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the hopes of another life is that onely which maketh one happy in this life, and the want of it moſt miſerable: if hope were confined onely to this life, man then were more miſerable then beaſts, and Chriſtians that adventure moſt for Chriſt, were more miſerable then other men: which abſurditie is ſo groſſe againſt the light of Nature without, and conſcience within, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle addeth no argument to refell it. For the firſt.</p>
            <p>That the Lord Jeſus, the foundation of the comforts we enjoy, or can expect, is the Chriſt the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the ſeed of the woman, promiſed to <hi>Adam,</hi> that ſhould breake the Serpents head.</p>
            <p>You heard in the forenoon, that he is a great King, and that his lawes are moſt equall, his ſubjects happieſt, having no other tax laid on them then love and feare, and to provide for themſelves by laying up a good foundation againſt the time to come. My Text holdeth him out, not onely as a <hi>great King,</hi> but as a <hi>great God;</hi> before whom the Kings and all the kingdomes of the World are <hi>but as the duſt of the balance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.15.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſmall drops of a bucket,</hi> he is the Chriſt, whom the Prophets called <hi>Meſſiah. Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 25,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113005:6"/>26. <hi>The Meſſiah the Prince ſhall be ſlaine, and the Meſſiah ſhall be cut off,</hi> and in the 2 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> compared with <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.26.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in one place he is called the <hi>Lords Meſſiah,</hi> in the other, the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> the Greek interpreters render it <hi>Meſſias,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Solent in peregrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulis Graeci ultimam conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantem in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> mutare, ſie <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ex <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daico</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The Jewes in all ages, but more eſpecially, when the fulnes of time was come, were raiſed in their expectations of him; <hi>Simeon</hi> waited for <hi>the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of Iſrael, Luk.</hi> 2.26. And <hi>Anna</hi> ſpake of him to all <hi>that looked for redemption in Iſrael, ver.</hi> 38. And not onely the <hi>Jewes,</hi> but the <hi>Samaritans</hi> alſo were lifted up with expectation of this great <hi>Meſſiah. Joh.</hi> 4.25. <hi>I know, ſaid the Samaritan woman, that the Meſſiah cometh, which is called Chriſt: and when he is come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ex</hi> Annibal <hi>Druſ.</hi> Obſer. l. 9. c. 9. Glaſ. pag. 138.</note> 
               <hi>he will tell us all things;</hi> and when <hi>Andrew</hi> had found him, he came to <hi>Peter,</hi> and told him that he <hi>had found the Meſſiah, which being interpreted, is the Chriſt:</hi> the one is Greek, the other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, both ſignifying, anointed; and if you aske what this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointing is? I anſwer, not onely the plenitude of gifts, whereby he was <hi>anointed with the oyl of gladneſſe above his fellowes, Pſal.</hi> 45.7. but the fulnes of the God-head. <hi>God gave him the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit without meaſure, Joh.</hi> 3.34. And as <hi>Peter</hi> in his Sermon to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> and other Gentiles, telleth how <hi>God preached peace by Chriſt Jeſus, who is Lord over all, ver.</hi> 36. <hi>And how God anointed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth with the Holy-Ghoſt and with power:</hi> and as it is ſaid in the 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 9. <hi>The fulneſſe of the God-head dwelleth</hi> in him <hi>bodily.</hi> This anointing intimateth both his Natures, that he was both God and man, and in both theſe Natures he was deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and anointed by the Father, to be King, Prieſt, and Prophet, to be Mediatour of an everlaſting Covenant.</p>
            <p>The Uſes of this point are:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, in reſpect of the judgement, to eſtabliſh that againſt two great errours, by which many in the world are ſeduced, and led away captive.</p>
            <p>One, of the Arians and Socinians, who ſo looke on his conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion when he became man, that they deny him to be God, as if he left to be what he was, when he tooke the nature he had not: it would be well if this errour were buried in everlaſting darkneſſe, never to be mentioned, but that many men blow theſe coals, to ſet not onely this kingdome, but the kingdome of Chriſt in a flame. The ſoule that beleeveth not this, that Chriſt is not onely a great
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113005:7"/>King, but a great God, is under the power of Satan, <hi>led caption according to his will.</hi> Satan may ſuggeſt, that it is a diſparagement to God the Father, to looke on Chriſt as God: but know that it is the delight of God the Father, that Chriſt ſhould be knowne, not onely to be a great King, but to be a great God; the Father calleth him ſo, <hi>thy throne â God is for ever and ever,</hi> and herein is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glorified,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.8.</note> that men glorifie the Sonne. There are ſour argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I will lay downe to fortifie you againſt this errour.</p>
            <p>The firſt Argument is taken from the peculiar names and titles that are appropriated to Chriſt, he is called God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.19. God manifeſt in the fleſh, and in the 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 6. though he were found in <hi>the forme of a Servant,</hi> yet he thought it <hi>no robberie to be equall</hi> with God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> But the name of God is appropriated to creatures:<note place="margin">Exod. 7.1. Pſal. 82.6.</note> God ſaith to <hi>Moſes, I have made thee a god to Pharaoh,</hi> and God ſaith of Princes and Nobles, I have ſaid ye are gods.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> To this I anſwer, that when the name of God is given to any creature, tis either with reſtrictive additions, as God ſaid to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Exod.</hi> 7.1. I have made thee a god to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> not a God to thy ſelfe, but <hi>to be inſtead of a god to Pharaoh, as he was to Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Exod.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Aaron ſhall be to thee thy mouth, and thou ſhall be to him in ſtead of God;</hi> or elſe it is given with reſtrictive dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutions, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. I have ſaid ye are gods, but ye ſhall die like men: but when Chriſt is called God, tis without any expreſſion that implyeth the leaſt diminution, but all additions ſerve for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirations: he is called not onely God, but firſt, the <hi>great God, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God,</hi> 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 13. not onely great, but ſecondly, <hi>mighty God, Iſa.</hi> 9.6. not onely mighty, but thirdly, <hi>almighty God, Revel.</hi> 4.8. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. Yea fourthly, <hi>God bleſſed</hi> for ever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. fifthly, the <hi>God of truth,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.20. Yea that great title <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which the Jewes hold<note n="a" place="margin">Fecit bujus nominis maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas, ut a priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Iudeis pro <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> haberetur: qui ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atione reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ergò abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuerunt: &amp; legerunt pro eo Adonaj. Glaſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pag. <hi>15.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> is not to be given to any meere creature, and which the Scripture ſetteth downe, as the name of God alone, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.18. is frequently given to Chriſt, this is the name where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſhall be called, <hi>the Lord our righteouſnes,</hi> or<note n="b" place="margin">Jer. 33 16.</note> 
               <hi>Jehovah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> righteouſnes, Jer.</hi> 23.6. If then the titles of the Father be given to Chriſt, tis no diminution of the Fathers glory, to acknowledge Chriſt God equall with the Father.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113005:7"/>
            <p>Secondly, conſider the attributes of Chriſt, and you ſhall finde the incommunicable accributes of God, which cannot be given to any meere creature, given to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he is eternall, I was <hi>ſet up from everlasting, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, before ever the Earth was,</hi> before he prepared the world, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.22. Surely none can be eternall but God;<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.1.</note> 
               <hi>from everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to everlaſting thou art God;</hi> but the Lord Jeſus Chriſt he is eternall, Out of <hi>Bethlchem Ephrata</hi> ſhall come out <hi>to me he that is</hi> to be <hi>ruler in Iſrael, whoſe goings forth have been from of old, from everlaſting, Mic.</hi> 5.2. Compared with, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.6. and therefore, when Chriſt had finiſhed the worke of our Redemption, he prayed that the Father would glorify him with himſelfe, <hi>with the glory</hi> which he had with him, <hi>before the beginning</hi> of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is not onely eternall, but immutable, the fame <hi>ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday,</hi> to day, and for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly he is omnipreſent, and ſurely he that filleth the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the Earth, muſt needs be God: but Chriſt was in Heaven, while he was on Earth: <hi>The Sonne of man which is in Heaven, Joh.</hi> 3.13. he is with his people in all ages, in all places, <hi>to the end of the world. Math.</hi> 28.10. I am with you to the end of the world, <hi>he</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>liveth in them,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.3.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeaketh in them,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>walketh in them,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>dwelleth in them,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>filleth them all in all,</hi> therefore ſurely he muſt needs be God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he is omnipotent, the Lord God omnipotent, ſo called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17. and Chriſt ſpeaking of himſelfe, ſaith, I am the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega, &amp;c.</hi> which is, <hi>and which was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1.8.</note> and which is to come, the Almighty.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, he is omniſcient, he is the wiſedome of God, in him are all <hi>treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge, Col.</hi> 2.3. <hi>he knoweth all things, Joh. laſt</hi> 20. Seatcheth all things, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. compated with <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. laſt, <hi>he needed not that any man ſhould testifie of man, for he knew what was in man:</hi> he foretelleth all the changes which ſhall come upon the ſonnes of men, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.11. compared with <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.19. <hi>I have told you, before it come to paſſe; that when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to paſſe, ye may beleeve</hi> that I am he, you can name no other eſſentiall Attribute of God, but it is given unto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, looke on the workes of Chriſt, and theſe prove him to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113005:8"/>be God, it was his argument to the Jawes, when they asked him, How <hi>long wilt thou make us to doubts tell us plainly if thou be the Christ:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 10.24.25</note> he anſwered, The works that I have done in my fathers name, they teſtifie of me, <hi>and beleeve me, for the very works ſake, Joh.</hi> 14.11.</p>
            <p>Conſider amongſt the workes of God:</p>
            <p>Firſt, the workes of creation: ſurely he that laid the foundation of the earth, and ſtretched out the heaven like a curtaine, muſt needs be God, for the <hi>gods that have not made the Heaven and the Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>even they ſhall periſh from the Earth, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> It is God that made the Earth by his owne power, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the World by his owne wiſdome; now all things were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by him, that are in Heaven and Earth, viſible and inviſible, <hi>&amp;c. Col.</hi> 1.16. and not onely by him, but for him, and <hi>without him was nothing made of all that was made:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 1.3.</note> and ſurely, power to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate being infinite, is ſo proper to the Creatour, that it is incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable to any creature, for no finite creature can be capable of an infinite power.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider his workes of ſuſtaining all things, all this glorious world would be turned into a Chaos, were it not that Chriſt ſuſtaineth all things by the word of his power, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. and he was <hi>not onely before all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.17. Joh. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>but by him all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt;</hi> my Father, ſaith Chriſt, worketh <hi>hitherto, and I worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider the workes of miracles in the dayes of his fleſh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.10. <hi>thou art great,</hi> and doeſt wondrous things, thou art God alone; the ſeas and winds obeyed him, the ſpirits came out of the poſſeſſed, and though the Apoſtles did great miracles, yet it was not in their owne name, as themſelves confeſſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.12. &amp; 4.10. and by this Argument Chriſt ſatisfied <hi>Johns</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, Go tell what things ye heare and ſee, the blinde receive <hi>their ſight, the lame walke, the lepers are cleanſed, and the deaf heart, and the dead are raiſed, &amp;c.</hi> and ſtopped the mouth of the Jewes, If I had not done amongſt them thoſe workes that no man had done, they had not had ſinnne, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.24.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Conſider the workes of Chriſt as Mediatour, he that reneweth the heart of man,<note place="margin">Job. 14.4.</note> and bringeth <hi>a cleane thing, out of an uncleane,</hi> and darkenes out of light, he that can circumciſe the heart, and purifie to himſelfe a peculiar people, muſt needs be God,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113005:8"/>he that pardoneth iniquity, ſinne and tranſgreſſion, muſt needs be God, for who can forgive ſinnes but God? <hi>Mark.</hi> 2.5, 7. he that was the Sonne of man, had power on Earth to forgive ſinnes, and therefore muſt needs be God, <hi>Math</hi> 9.6. and the lamb of God that taketh a way the ſinnes of the world; he that is the captaine of our Salvation, that redeemeth his people from death and Hell, and hath deſtroyed him that had power over death, muſt needs be more then meer man, for no man can redeem his brother from death, but onely Chriſt, who hath the keys of hell <hi>and death, Rev.</hi> 1.18.</p>
            <p>The fourth Argument is taken from the great prerogatives and preheminences proper to God, <hi>God is a jealous God, and will not give his glory to any creature, Iſa.</hi> 42.8. &amp; 48.11. but all glory that belongeth unto God the Father, the Father hath commanded us to give it unto the Sonne, <hi>that all men might honour the Sonne, as they honour the Father: he that honoureth not the Sonne, honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Father, Joh.</hi> 5.23. We are baptized into the name of the Father, and ſo are we into the name of the Sonne, and not into the name of any creature: we are bound to pray to God the Father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.32. and ſo are we bound to pray unto God the Sonne, <hi>Stephen called upon the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7.59. Act. 9.13. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with ver. 21.</note> and the Saints are deſcribed <hi>to be ſuch, as call upon the name of Jeſus:</hi> we are bound to beleeve in the name of the Sonne, as well as in the name of the Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14 1. we are commanded to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. compared with <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23. all acts of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that are proper to the Father, are given to the Sonne, and when he bringeth his firſt begotten into the world, he biddeth <hi>all the Angells worſhip him, Heb.</hi> 1.6. now, worſhip is onely proper to God: we are bound to love Chriſt above all, to ſweare by him, and not by any creature: now if all the titles, all the attributes of God, all the peculiar workes, and incommunicable priviledges of the Father, be communicated to the Sonne, we may be confident that Jeſus Chriſt is not onely the Sonne of man, but the Sonne of God, yea God himſelfe bleſſed for ever more.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Errour we are to be eſtabliſhed againſt, is that of the Jewes, who having ſlain the Lord of Glory, and the Prince of life, are ſtill expecting the Meſſiah, denying Jeſus the Sonne of <hi>Mary</hi> to be that promiſed ſeed: tis good, not only to know their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113005:9"/>errour, but to be eſtabliſhed againſt it, and to know him who we do beleeve, that he is the Meſſiah, able to ſave to the utmoſt: to this end conſider theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> The firſt Argument is from the time that Jeſus Chriſt came in the fleſh, it was according to all the prophecies, <hi>when the Scepter was departed from Judah,</hi> when the expectation of the Jewes was raiſed,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> in <hi>looking for the redemption, and conſolation in Iſrael,</hi> in thoſe mournfull dayes, wherein <hi>Rachel</hi> was weeping for her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>it was after that Elijah was come,</hi> and as a meſſenger went before his face, it was after the determination of the 70. weeks, <hi>viz.</hi> the 490. years determined upon the people, till the Meſſiah ſhould be ſlaine, all this proveth that he came in that moment and juncture of time, wherein he was promiſed by the Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Conſider the place of Chriſts birth, <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, Mic.</hi> 5.1. compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.6. the place whither he was driven after his birth, to <hi>Egypt,</hi> the place where he dwelt after his returne from <hi>Egypt,</hi> at <hi>Nazareth, Math.</hi> 2.22. the Jewes rejected him upon this ground, becauſe he lived in <hi>Galilee,</hi> they ſaid, ſhall Chriſt come out of <hi>Galilee? Joh.</hi> 7.41. and were ſo confident, that they bad <hi>Nicodemus</hi> ſearch and looke,<note place="margin">Joh. 7.52.</note> for <hi>out of Galilee ariſeth no Prophet,</hi> whereas the expreſſe prophecies run, that by the way of the Sea beyond <hi>Jordan</hi> in <hi>Galilee</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the people that walked in darknes, have ſeen a great light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.1. compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, Conſider the manner of his converſing, the Jewes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a Meſſiah, that ſhould be a glorious champion, who by fire and ſword ſhould ſubdue Nations and Kingdomes: but you may obſerve that this and all other arguments, whereby the Jewes are miſ-led to deny him, are as a firme foundation for this truth, and our confidence: aske a Jew, why doe you not beleeve Jeſus to be the Meſſiah? is it becauſe he came not as a man of warre? how ſhould he then be the Prince of peace, of whom it was foretold, he ſhall not cry, <hi>nor lift up his voice, nor cauſe it to be heard</hi> in the ſtreets? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.2. &amp; <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9. God pointeth the Church there to the Meſſiah, Behold thy king cometh unto thee, meek and lowly, having Salvation, riding upon an aſſe, and the foal of an aſſe, compared with <hi>Math.</hi> 21.8. doe you therefore reject him, becauſe he was not honoured of men?<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.3.</note> therefore the rather acknowledge him to be the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113005:9"/>Meſſiah, <hi>who is deſpiſed and rejected of men,</hi> for thus ſaith the Lord of him whom man deſpiſeth, <hi>unto him whom the Nation abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 49.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, Conſider the things he ſuffered. The Jewes argue, Can he be the Meſſiah that was condemned by the High Prieſt, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his owne Diſciples, had his garments divided,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> had his body crucified? and upon this miſtake, the Jewes blaſpheme the name of the Lord Jeſus in their Synagogues, under the name of one that is<note n="*" place="margin">Patibulo affixue interijte Quid iſtud ad cauſam? vid. <hi>Arnob.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> hanged, and this alſo was the ſtumbling block of the heathen: but all theſe are Arguments to convince us, that he is the Meſſiah, Ought not Chriſt firſt to ſuffer theſe things, and then to enter into his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? was not he the ſtone which the builders refuſed? did not God foretell us of him? I will ſmite the ſhepherd, and the flock ſhall be ſcattered, and that the Jewes <hi>ſhould ſmite the Judge of Iſrael</hi> with a rod upon his cheek, <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.1. doth not the Meſſiah ſay, I gave my back to the ſmiters, <hi>and I hid</hi> not my ſelfe from ſhame and ſpitting? have ye not read that they pierced my hands and feet,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> and upon my veſture they caſt lots? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.19. tis written, that it pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him, and put him to grief, when thou ſhalt make his ſoule an offering for ſin, he ſhall ſee his ſeed, and ſhall prolong his dayes, and the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand, he ſhall ſee the travell of his ſoule, and ſhall be ſatifyed.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Arg.</hi> Fifthly, Conſider his Reſurrection, for he was declared mightily to be the Sonne of God, by the reſurrection from the dead,<note place="margin">Math. 26.42.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. the Jewes, when he hung on the croſſe, ſaid, <hi>let him come downe from the croſſe,</hi> and we will beleeve him, tis <hi>Jeroms</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:<note n="*" place="margin">Fran dulenta promiſſio, quid eſt plue, de cruce ad bue viventem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendere, an de ſepulchro mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum reſurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re? <hi>Hieron</hi> in <hi>Math 26.</hi>
               </note> this promiſe of theirs was fraudulent, for whether was it more to come downe from the croſſe when he was alive, or to riſe from the grave when he was dead? yet he aroſe and they beleeved him not, and when he was in the Sepulchre, they ſaid, This decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid he would riſe, but we will make the Sepulchre ſure, but it were impoſſible for him to be held of death.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Conſider even the confeſſions. of his adverſaries, <hi>Pilat</hi> who condemned him, could not but acknowledge he found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worthy of death in him,<note n="b" place="margin">Non poſſum dignè admirari pro rei magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine, quod redemptis pre. tio falſit teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; ad ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem populo concitato, rul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam aliam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerint cauſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> interſectionts e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, niſequod Rex Iudaeorum eſset. Illi ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanilludentes hoc fecerint, ſed Pilaius etiam nolentibue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponder, Quod ſcripſi, ſcripſi. <hi>Hieron</hi> ibid.</note> It was admirable when all falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe were hired, and the people ſtirred up with indignation, and yet the Judge that is drawne to condemne him, could not be drawne to give any other reaſon of his condemnation, then that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113005:10"/>he was the king of the Jewes, and his paſſion was accompanied with that terrour, darknes covered the Earth, the vaile was torne aſunder, and the Rocks rent, the Graves opened, and the ſunne ſo darkned, that one of the heathen cryed out, Either the God of nature now ſuffereth, or the fabrick of the world will preſently be diſſolved; and the Centurion, and thoſe that were with him watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jeſus, ſaw the Earthquake, and thoſe things that were done, and feared greatly, ſaying, <hi>Truly this was the Sonne of God:</hi> 'tis a wonder that the Centurion, even before the Croſſe, when he was under the ſcandall of his paſſion, ſhould confeſſe him to be God, and that any Chriſtians after his Reſurrection, ſhould affirme him to be meer man.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Conſider the judgements that are come upon the Jewes:<note place="margin">M. Fox his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</note> it was an argument that convinced one Jew here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> about 80. yeares ſince; they ſaid, his blood be on us, and on our ſeed, and what they wiſhed wantonly, God hath poured out upon them extreamely, for theſe 1600. yeares they have been a ſcattered people, God hath kept them a diſtinct people, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his people by anothe name: in times of their other judgements, God gave them Prophets, <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Ezra, Nehemiah, &amp;c.</hi> in the Captivitie: but ſince they have had no Prophet, no viſion, and the reaſon why God keepeth them a diſtinct people, ſince their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion, whereas other ations, when they have been ſcattered, have been ſo mixed, that their originalls hath been ſcarce diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhable, is, that as their curſe and confuſion is remarkable, ſo their converſion might be diſtinct and admirable, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall take to himſelfe his great power, and rule gloriouſly; and their bringing in will be ſuch a cleer conviction to the Nations, that they ſhall come into the brightnes of Chriſts riſing.</p>
            <p>I might add in the eighth place, the carrying on the Goſpell by the weakeſt meanes, againſt the mightieſt oppoſition: other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions are carryed on by an arme of fleſh, and humane policy: but God in the ſpreading the Goſpell, ſet folly to contend with wefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and weaknes with ſtrength, that the excellency <hi>of the power might be of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>and not of men,</hi> and when all the kings of the Earth would have cruſhed it in its infancy, and ſtrangled it in the wombe, there being nothing for three hundred yeares, but rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, tortures, fire and fagot, yet the blood <hi>of the Martyrs</hi> was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113005:10"/>the ſeed of the Church, and the <hi>more they were lopt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plures effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, quoties metimur. <hi>Terrul.</hi> Apol. <hi>Zach. 4.6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the more</hi> they grew, and there were never more glorious Saints then in thoſe times of darknes, to make it appeare, that the Kingdome of Chriſt was not carryed on by <hi>power, nor by might, but by the ſpirit of the Lord of Hosts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Is Jeſus Chriſt the great God,<note place="margin">Uſe 2 of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> then be exhorted firſt to ſtudy the excellencie of Jeſus Chriſt, how tranſcendenlty admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is he? ſurely, all the Kings and Kingdomes of the world are to him but <hi>as the drop of a bucket, and the dust of the balance:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.15.</note> did you but ſee the Sun of Righteouſneſſe, no ſtarre elſe would appeare: it would be happy if men and women that profeſſe Chriſt, were taken with the admiration of Jeſus Chriſt: did they but once know what Chriſt is, they would count all loſſe to winne him: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why many things ſeeme <hi>ſo great</hi> to our thoughts, is becauſe Chriſt <hi>ſeemes little,</hi> if Chriſt were really apprehended of us, it would ſeem a ſmall thing to us to be jadged of men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Be willing to cloſe with Chriſt, to accept of him: Shall he be willing to come from Heaven, to take your nature upon him? and are ye unwilling to come out of ſin and Hell, to partake of his divine nature? this unwillingnes for Chriſt is the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning ſin of the world: can any of you anſwer the ſlighting the Lord Jeſus, that he ſhould be willing to take your ſhame on him, and you not willing to partake of his grace and glory? The Jew would have a Meſſiah, for temporall ends, to breake the Romane power: and the carnall Chriſtian for a carnall end, that he might ſin with immunity, and commit ſin without feare, and turne the grace of God into wantonnes. Hath Chriſt come to deliver you from the power of Satan, and will you yet be under the power of your owne luſts?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If Chriſt be this great Meſſiah, exalt him,</p>
            <p>Firſt, In your opinions of him, have not meane thoughts of the God of Glory, count his arguments <hi>the ſtongeſt,</hi> his precepts to be the pureſt, his comforts to be the ſweeteſt, his rewards to be the higheſt, his people to be the happieſt, that you may be able to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the wayes of Chriſt, againſt all the arguments of corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the temptations of this preſent evil world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Exalt him in your affections, let the deſires of your ſoule be to him, and to the remembrance of his name, that you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113005:11"/>may ſay, and ſay truly, Lord, whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there is none in Earth that I deſire beſides thee, let him be the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of you ſouls, that you may ſay, <hi>my belove is mine, and I am his,</hi> ſet him up as the joy and rejoycing of your hearts, that you may ſay,<note place="margin">Pſal 43.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto God will I goe, even unto God, the gladnes of my joy:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bſ.8.13.</note> magnifie him in your hearts, and let him be <hi>your feare and your dread,</hi> and if he be God bleſſed for ever, make him the God of your confidence, never be aſhamed of him, in whom you doe beleeve;<note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> and if he be God, be then fully perſwaded that he is able to ſave <hi>them to the utmoſt that come unto God</hi> through him, and make him the God of your hope and expectation, pour out your ſoules before him, and ſay, God is our hope: and this leadeth me to the ſecond Obſervation.</p>
            <p>All thoſe that would have benefit by Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Doct.</note> muſt be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto him, and ſet their hopes upon him. Our hopes are not in our ſelves, nor in the creature, in vaine is ſalvation hoped for <hi>from</hi> the hills,<note place="margin">Jet. 3.23.</note> 
               <hi>and from the multitude of mountaines,</hi> truly the Lord God is our hope, and the ſalvation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and happy is he that hath the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> for his helpe, whoſe hope is in the Lord his God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.5. the Doctrine needeth not ſo much explication to cleere the Judgement, as application to better our practice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>
               </label> The Uſe therefore is, firſt to intreate you to make Chriſt your hope, this is the great duty God requireth, one great end of all the great things he hath done for you in his <hi>workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.7.</note> that you <hi>might ſet your hopes upon him,</hi> and of the good things he hath revealed to you in his word,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> that through <hi>the Scriptures you might have hope,</hi> and not onely have it,<note place="margin">ver. 13.</note> but have it in abundance, that you <hi>might abound in hope, through the power of the Holy ghoſt:</hi> this is the great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge God beſtoweth on them that are good in his ſight, <hi>thou art my hope in the day of evil, Jer.</hi> 17.17. this hope is to the ſoule, as the <hi>Helmet</hi> is to the ſouldier,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.8.</note> to cover his head in the day of battel, and as an <hi>Anchor</hi> to the ſhip in a mighty ſtorme,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.19.</note> it is our hiding place, our Citie, and our rock of refuge, and <hi>they alone have</hi> ſtrong <hi>conſolation, who flee</hi> for refuge to the hope ſt before them, and by this hope enter within the vaile, whither the forerunner is before entred: that this might dwell upon your hearts, give me leave to propound a few motives.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>1</label> Conſider, firſt the neceſſity of hope, no man without it can live contentedly, or die comfortably.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113005:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, No man can live contentedly, aske your owne ſoules, doe you thinke that any of you can live either <hi>rationally</hi> as men, or <hi>uſefully</hi> as Magiſtrates, or <hi>ſpiritually</hi> as Chriſtians?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Doe you thinke that any can live rationally, as men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope: life without hope may be ſenſuall, like to the life of beaſts. made to be taken and to be deſtroyed, but it cannot be rationall, for reaſon teacheth us ſo to uſe things <hi>temporall,</hi> as to provide for things <hi>eternall.</hi> What content can there be to a man of reaſon, without hope, when he conſidereth either the <hi>deficiency</hi> of the good he enjoyeth, or the <hi>eminency</hi> of the evil he feareth?</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the deficiency of good, looke on the ſonnes of men, that ſeeme to themſelves and others the happieſt under the ſun, and you ſhall eaſily perceive this truth, firſt, that no condition of men is ſo compleatly good, as to be without a mixture of evil: there are ſome graines of gall and wormwood, to allay the ſweetnes of the moſt delightfull potion; and though this beitternes for a few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be concealed from ſenſe, yet it is cleare to reaſon, whenn man reflecteth inwardly, and communeth with his owne heart. <hi>Solomon</hi> when he returned to himſelfe, judged the comfort that before ſeemed moſt admitable, to be moſt contemptible, crying out, Vanitie of vanities, allthings underthe ſun were butvanitie,<note place="margin">Ecccleſ. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>full of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that man could not utter it:</hi> the eye being not ſatisfied with ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor the eare with hearing: therefore all the good things of this world, being in themſelves incompleat, can never give to the ſoule compleat contentment; for nothing can act above its one ſphere.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Suppoſe the condition of ſome on man of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, to be ſo good, as to be free from any conſiderable mixture of evil; yet no-condition here below, but is capable of a meliora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: it is not ſo good, but it may be better: ſo hope is ſtill need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that all fruitions might be heightened by expectations.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the condition be ſuch, that thy ſoule doth nott wiſh it to be better, yet thy heart may juſtly feare it may be worſe, and ſo there is ever need of hope, if not for a new addition of ſome good you have not, yet for the continuance of all the good you have, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe when you ſay your mountaine is the ſtrongeſt, then deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation may be the neereſt; and when there is the higheſt <hi>lifting up,</hi> then you may meet with the ſaddeſt caſting downe: when <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> ſaid, Is not this great <hi>Babel</hi> which I have built for my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113005:12"/>ſelfe? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then came there a voice from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is departed from thee,<note place="margin">Dan. 4 31.</note> &amp;c.</hi> and when the rich man in the Goſpell began to feed upon ſenſe, without hope, and ſaid, Soule take thine eaſe: he had that ſad anſwer returned, <hi>foole, this night ſhall thy ſoule be taken from thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the eminencie of evil: beſides that there is a mixture of evil for the preſent, with allgood: whereby it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to paſle, that all your comforts laid in the balance, can ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly equall your diſeomforts; yet conſider, <hi>all the evil you feel for the preſent, is nothing to what you may feare for the future;</hi> and it is not ſo ill to day, but it may grow worſe to morrow: we had need to remember our Creator in out beſt time, before the evil dayes come in which we ſhall ſay, we have no pleaſure in them, and when after all ſtormes and tempeſt ſtill, <hi>the cloudes ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne after the raine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider the ſadnes of theſe dayes: the Lord hath made the glory <hi>of our Jacob thin,<note place="margin">Iſa. 17.4.</note> and the fatnes of his fleſh to wax leane,</hi> and a great fire is kindled under all our glory. How are the eſtates of many great men emptied? how many <hi>Naomies</hi> out of every Countrey, that ſay, <hi>Call me not Naomi, but Marah?</hi> how is the greatnes of men diminiſhed? how are their honours overclouded? the day of the <hi>Lord of Hoſts is not onely on the Bryars and Buſhes, buton all the Cedars of Lebanon that are high and lifted up, and upon all the Oaks of Baſhan,<note place="margin">Iſa, 2.13.</note> upon all the high mountaines, and upon all the hills that are lifted up;</hi> God calleth upon all the ſonnes of men, Enter into the rock, and hide your ſelves in the duſt, for feare of the Lord, and the glory of his Majeſty, when he ariſeth to ſhalke terribly the the Earth; whe had never more terrours <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> God raineth downe upon us feares and ſnares, and an horrible tempeſt, and therefore we had never more need of hopes <hi>within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Without hope great men cannot live uſefully, as Magiſtrates: when God hath made any of the ſonnes of men great, it is hard not to be great in their owne eyes: this aſlure your ſelfe of, that though you are greater, <hi>yet your corruptions are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fewer:</hi> Originall ſin is in all men equall: <hi>your diverſions for the moſt part are greater:</hi> you have ſo much company of others, as that you have little time to commune with your owne hearts: your <hi>temptations are stronger:</hi> the greater you are, Satanoweth you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113005:12"/>the greater ſpite: few have been made better by greatnes: how many men doe all ages tell us of, who have been made worſe? there are many flatterers, and but few admoniſhers. It was <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> unhappines in the midſt of all his glory,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.28.</note> 
               <hi>that he found ſcarce one man in a thouſand faithfull;</hi> adde to this, that <hi>your engagements</hi> to God <hi>are greater;</hi> your <hi>falles,</hi> if you miſcarrie, <hi>more exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> your <hi>account</hi> unto the great God, <hi>more dreadfull; you have I knowne, ſaith God, above all the people of the Earth, therefore you will I puniſh for your iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, No man can live ſpiritually, as a Chriſtian, without hope, every Chriſtian beſides the combats he muſt meet with, <hi>as man.</hi> hath other combats he muſt undergoe, <hi>as a Christian;</hi> his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all combat is ſtronger, not onely with temptations without, but with corruptions within: his thoughts are higher, his feares are lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, his care is not onely how to be ſecure in mans day, but how he may be delivered from ſinne, and death and hell, how he may ſtand faſt <hi>in the day of evil.</hi> What is it that can make a poore ſonle enter into this combat, continue in this conflict, deſpiſe this world, deny himſelfe, runne thorow all ſtraits, triumph over all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but onely hope? which cauſeth us to ſee, <hi>that the light afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this world, which is but for a moment, Worketh for us a farre more excellent, and eternall weight of glory: whilſt we looke not on the things that are ſeen, but on the things that are not ſeen: for the things that are ſeen, are temporall, but the things that are not ſeen, are eternall,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.17, 18.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As no man can <hi>live contentedly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secondly, no man can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortably without hope.</note> ſo no man can <hi>die com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably</hi> without hope. Who can expreſle the darkneſſe of that ſoul that liveth <hi>without feare, and dyeth without hope?</hi> when all joy is darkened, and all glory goeth downe under a dark cloud, and all comforts end in a ſtorme, which never bloweth over; when you muſt leave the condition <hi>you know,</hi> for a condition <hi>which you know not;</hi> when you muſt leave a <hi>certainty</hi> for to goe upon a <hi>contigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> when the poor wandring trembling ſoul, is unable to ſtay in, and unwilling to goe out, when the ſoule goeth upon eternity, not knowing whither; when the body muſt goe to ly under the ſlimic valley, that before lay upon <hi>beds of lvorie;</hi> and the eyes that ſaw the glory of the world, muſt never ſee light any more; and the eares which before heard delightfull muſique, muſt now be for ever ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113005:13"/>better never to have come into the world, then to goe out of it without hope: a <hi>Roman</hi> may die <hi>patiently, and harden his heart againſt ſorrow; but onely a Christian, through hope, can die trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly, crying out Oh death where is thy ſting, Oh grave where is thy victorie,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55.</note> &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>2</label> Secondly, as no man can live or die without hope, and this ſnoweth the neceſſity of it ſo no hope can carry us thorow all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, but hope in Chriſt: thinke but on the inſufficiency of the creature, the vanity of all other hopes: without hope there is <hi>no ſulſiſtonce,</hi> and without Chriſt hope cannot <hi>ſubſiſt:</hi> if you muſt hope, where will you place this hope? you cannot rationally ſettle this hope, either <hi>in your ſelf,</hi> or in any <hi>other creature: not in your ſelf:</hi> for what is there in your ſelf, that can be a rationall ground of hope? not your parts, though never ſo great, they may be <hi>ſoon blaſted,</hi> are often <hi>greatly poyſoned,</hi> and if they continue in their greateſt luſtre, they may be overpow'rd: <hi>Huſhai goeth beyound Achitophel,</hi> and the wiſeſt of men have found <hi>the steps of their owne ſtrength straitned,<note place="margin">Job. 18.7.</note> and their owne counſels to caſt them downe:</hi> this hope cannot be in <hi>your eſtates,</hi> they are not ſo full, but they may be ſoon emptie:<note place="margin">Pro. 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>wilt thou ſet thine eyes on that which is not? riches take to themſelves wings, and ſtee away:</hi> and ſurely their wings were never <hi>longer,</hi> nor their ſlight <hi>ſwifter,</hi> then in theſe dayes:<note place="margin">Pſa. 62.10.</note> 
               <hi>truſt not in oppreſſion, become not vaine in robbery: if rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es increaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them; hope not in your names,</hi> they may be overclouded: God in a moment can ſtaine the glory and pride of all fleſh, abhorre the excellency of <hi>Jacob,</hi> he lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>counſellours away ſpoyled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 11.27,</note> and overthroweth the mighty, he taketh away the underſtanding of the aged, <hi>he poureth contempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Princes, and weakneth the ſtrength of the mighty: he increaſeth the Nations,</hi> and deſtroyeth them, he enlargeth the nations and ſtraitneth them againe, he taketh away the <hi>hearts of the</hi> chiefe of the people of the Earth, and cauſeth them to wander in a wildernes where there is no way, ſo they grope in the dark without light, and he maketh them to ſtagger like a drunken man: and as there is no <hi>ground of hope in your ſelf,</hi> ſo there is no ground of hope <hi>in the creature:</hi> hath not God diſappointed many of us of our hopes? <hi>doe we notroare like bears, and mourne like doves; doe we not grope for the wall like blinde men,<note place="margin">Iſa. 59.10, 11.</note> groping as if we had no eyes?</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113005:13"/>have we not often looked for ſalvation, but it is not? Conſider the minde <hi>of man is variable,</hi> we change our counſells as ſick men change their beds, imputing all our diſappointments, rather to any one then to our ſelves: and as the minde of man is variable, ſo the <hi>ſtrength of crentures is expugnable,</hi> ſo that the whole frame of nature is a bed too narrow for one to <hi>ſtretch himſelf upon it,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.20.</note> and a covering too narrow for one to wrap himſelfe in it:</hi> all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſun are but vanity;<note place="margin">Job. 15.31.</note> 
               <hi>and let not him that is deceived truſt in vanity, for vanity ſhall be his recompence:</hi> we may faltter out ſelves to our ruine, under theſe ſeduced hopes; but all theſe hopes in the iſſue will prove but as a <hi>ſiders web,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.14 &amp; 11.20. &amp; 18.14. &amp; 27.8.</note> and as the <hi>giving up of the Ghoſt,</hi> and all humane confidence will bring th ſoule to <hi>the king of terrours,</hi> and what <hi>hope can a bypocrite have, when God taketh away his ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſid. </seg>3</label> The third Conſideration to move you to ſet your hopes on Chriſt, let it be from the <hi>allſufficiency of Chriſt;</hi> there is this vaſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt hope in Chriſt, and hope in the Creature: from the creature you cannot expect <hi>ſo little,</hi> but you ſhall <hi>finde leſſe</hi> then you doe expect: from Chriſt you cannot expect <hi>ſo much,</hi> but you ſhall <hi>receive more</hi> then you doe expect:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.20.</note> He is able to doe <hi>abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, above all that we are albe to ask or think:</hi> all ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are in him alone, he it is alone that can ſay, I will make you free from your luſts and temptations, from death and hell, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can ſay, I will pardon your iniquities, cure your diſeaſes, take the ſtony heart out os you, <hi>I will write my law in you,<note place="margin">Ezek. 36.26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9.</note> and ye ſhall all be taught of God:</hi> I will beſtow my Heaven on you, my throne, my kingdome, and ſuch joyes <hi>as Eye hath not ſeen, nor Eare heard, nor can it ever enter into the heart of man to conceive.</hi> What an admirable thing is it, that a poor ſoul may come and ſay, What may ſuch a one as I am be pardoned, that am condemned? may my infirmity be cured, when the ſoare <hi>runneth</hi> and <hi>ceaſeth not?</hi> may this loathſome leproſy be healed? what a comfort is it to a poor ſoul, that he may come to Chriſt as the poor leper, and ſay, <hi>Lord, if thou wilt, whou canſt make me whole;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 8.2.</note> Beſides in this world, he alone is <hi>able</hi> to ſupply <hi>all your wants,</hi> anſwer all <hi>your doubts,</hi> ſeatter all your <hi>feares:</hi> and he is not onely able, but hath engaged himſelfe by promiſe, to all <hi>that hope in his mercy;</hi> he calleth to you, <hi>get ye to the strong holds, ye priſoners of hope:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 9.12.</note> he biddeth you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113005:14"/>caſt all your care on him,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.7.</note> for he careth <hi>for you;</hi> and be not diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted about the things of this life, as other Gentiles that know not God,<note place="margin">Math. 6.32.</note> 
               <hi>for your heavenly father knoweth what you have need of:</hi> will you truſt him for your ſoules, and not for your bodies? will you truſt him for Eternity, and not for a moment? will you truſe him to deliver you from the rage of devils? and not from the rage of men?<note place="margin">Pſal. 97.2.</note> roll your ſoules upon him, and he will carry you in his boſome; and though <hi>clouds and darknes be round about him,</hi> yet you ſhall ſee that righteouſnes and judgement <hi>are the habitation of his throne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.17.</note> your eyes ſhall ſee the <hi>king in his beauty,</hi> that he is <hi>a defender</hi> above all <hi>destroyers:</hi> you ſhall be upon <hi>a Rock higher then waves;</hi> we meet here with great difficulties, and thoſe cauſe great feares, and great feares had need of great hope, and theſe are never <hi>great enough</hi> but in the <hi>great God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Augaſtin.</hi> Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>44.</hi> De ipſis amar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinibus mur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, dich, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce pereunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Chriſtianis temporthus, quid ſtreqis? non boc promiſit Deus, qu ed iſta non peribunt: Aeterna pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſit aelernus, &amp;c.</note> Chriſt alone can make us above <hi>our ſelves,</hi> above <hi>men,</hi> above <hi>changes,</hi> above the <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> of this preſent evil world: why doth the ſoule which hopeth in Chriſt complain that the world changeth? did ever God <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that it ſhould not change?</hi> hath not God tould us expreſſely, that the <hi>Heavens wax old as a garment</hi> and as a veſture, ſhall he change them, <hi>and they ſhall be changed:</hi> he that is <hi>eternall, hath promiſed things eternall:</hi> and if thou beleeve, of mortall, thou ſhalt be made immortall: and in the hopes of immortality, may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt triumph over whatſoever is mortall, ſaying as he did, <hi>World, why doſt thou fume? what wouldſt thou do if thou ſhouldſt continue, if ſo proud when thou hast no abiding?</hi> whom wouldſt thou not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive if thou <hi>wert ſweet,</hi> if thou haſt <hi>deceived</hi> ſo many whilſt <hi>thou art bitter?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quid. ſtrepis numde? quid immu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia? quid face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſi maneres? Quem non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciperes dalcis, ſi amarus, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I come to the third part, <hi>the extent of this hope; viz.</hi> that the hope of a Chriſtian is not confined to this life; <hi>if we had only hope in this life, &amp;c.</hi> Hence ariſeth the third Doctrine, <hi>viz. That they that would ſet their hopes on Christ, muſt be perſwaded there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother life after this life; and in this life it is their duty to aſſure the hopes of a better.</hi> You reade in the Scripture not only of <hi>this world, but of the world to come:</hi> Chriſt telleth us of <hi>ſins</hi> that ſhall not be forgiven, neither in <hi>this life,</hi> nor in <hi>the life to come,</hi> Matth. 12.32. And Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>farre exalted above all principalities and powers,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> not only in this world, but in that which is to come;</hi> and that world is ſo farre above this world, that the thoughts of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113005:14"/>eternity are called <hi>the powers of the world to come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.5.</note> and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power all the things of this world. We reade of <hi>Judgement to come; Pauls</hi> Sermon before the great Governout was of this ſubject, and <hi>it made him to tremble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.25.1 Cor. 4.3. Rin. 2.5.</note> and <hi>that judgement</hi> is ſarre above the judgement of <hi>mans day:</hi> We reade of <hi>wrath to come,</hi> and all the wrath that is preſent, is nothing to the <hi>day of wrath, and the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the righteous judgement of God:</hi> the Sadduces who were none of the beſt of men, but a generation of vipers,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.7.1 Theſ. 1.10.</note> yet were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned <hi>to flee from the wrath to come:</hi> and the great triumph of the Apoſtle was, that God had delivered them from <hi>wrath to come.</hi> We reade of another life to come, and that is the great priviledge of godlineſſe, that it hath not only the promiſes <hi>of this life,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> but of that which is to come:</hi> and the great work of grace upon the heart, is to take us off from looking after <hi>things temporall,</hi> and to make us look after <hi>things eternall,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.16. It was the Apoſtles life; they looked not on things that <hi>are ſeen,</hi> but on things that <hi>are not ſeen.</hi> Men are never Chriſtians in good earneſt, till they be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fully of the things of eternity; and that poor ſeduced ſoul that reſolveth never to be perſwaded, hath no ground to think that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſhall be converted.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>Dives</hi> begg'd that one might <hi>go from the dead to tell his brethren on the earth, leſt they alſo ſhould come into the ſame place of torment;</hi> intimating the cauſe of his own ſin and eternall miſery; intimating that he was not perſwaded of this place of torment in his life, and therefore came down to this place of torment at his death. God hath made the viſion herein ſo plain, that every one that runneth may reade it; and he that hardneth his heart againſt <hi>Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> is left inexcuſable,<note place="margin">ver. 31.</note> and is irrecoverable, and would not be perſwaded though <hi>one</hi> ſhould <hi>ariſe from the dead.</hi> The Uſe of this point is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, If there be an other life beſides this life, then let us be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for all that world of unbelief that is in our nature; that our <hi>perſwaſions</hi> about the things of eternity are <hi>ſo weake,</hi> when Gods <hi>expreſſions</hi> are ſo <hi>ſtrong and clear;</hi> that we can beleeve the things of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and will not beleeve the things of <hi>faith;</hi> that we entertain the reports of men, and reject the reports of God:<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.9.</note> Surely <hi>if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the witneſſe of men, is not the witneſſe of God greater?</hi> this unbelief was the firſt ſin, and is the laſt ſin; the cauſe of our firſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie, and ground of our continued malignity: when Chriſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113005:15"/>intendeth to convert a ſoul unto himſelf, this is the great ſin where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Spirit of Chriſt convinceth the ſoul, and the Spirit never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth a <hi>comforter,</hi> but where he is a <hi>convincer;</hi> and the firſt work in converſion is laid in an act of conviction, and that conviction diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth the great <hi>ſin of unbelief,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 16.9.</note> and where Chriſt doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them <hi>of it,</hi> he wil condemn them <hi>for it:</hi> how often are we bidden to <hi>take heed of this spirit of unbelief,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note> in departing from the living God?</hi> nor can any man be an heir of life, who lieth under the power of unbelief: for will any man deny himſelf, croſſe his own appetite, take up Chriſts croſſe, to aſſure to himſelf a propriety to thoſe things, wherein he beleeveth there is no reality? the ſoul muſt firſt beleeve the excellency of the things in themſelves, before it make it its great deſign to get an intereſt in them: if the things of eternity were fully beleeved, what manner of <hi>perſons would men be, in all holineſſe of converſation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.11.</note> and did you really look on ſuch things, it would make you diligent to <hi>be found of him without ſpot and blameleſſe.</hi> In the next place;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Let this entreat you to abhorre all thoſe opinions that may any waies weaken this perſwaſion; hate to be under the power of them, and when the power of them is broken, reſiſt the remainders, that Satan may <hi>get no advantage againſt you;</hi> eſpecially fortifie your ſelves with ſtrong arguments againſt theſe two opinions, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away a great part of the men of the world captive: the firſt is, of the <hi>groſſe Atheiſt,</hi> the other of the <hi>Semi-atheiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is of the <hi>grand Atheiſt:</hi> how many are there that have the face of Chriſtians, but their hearts are heatheniſh? who reſolve there faith into meer reaſon, and their hopes, into ſight? Such were the Sadduces in Chriſts time,<note place="margin">Acts 23.8.</note> who denied <hi>Angels, and ſpirits, and the reſurrection:</hi> ſuch Were before Chriſt among the Prophets, as thoſe Epicures,<note place="margin">Iſa. 22.12.13.</note> who when the <hi>Lord called for weeping and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, behold joy and gladneſſe, ſlaying of oxen and killing of ſheep; eating fleſh, and drinking wine,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall die:</hi> ſuch were ſome after Chriſt in the daies of the Apoſtle, <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. of this chapter: <hi>Peter</hi> propheſieth that there ſhould be ſuch to the end of the world, wicked and profane men, ſcoffers,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhould walk after their own lusts, ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his comming, for ſince the fathers fell aſleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the creation.</hi> It was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113005:15"/>an article objected againſt one of the Popes in the Councell of <hi>Baſil,</hi> that he had often ſaid before divers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joannes 23.</hi> Saepe coram di. verſis praelatia pertinaciler, juadente dia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, aſſeruit, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam aternam nonne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aliam poſt banc, dixit animan bomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nucum corpore relinqui, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, Baſil</hi> Seſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>11</hi>
               </note> that were was no ſuch thing as eternall life: and <hi>Paul</hi> the third is reported to have ſaid, when he was dying; now he ſhould know three things, whether the ſoul was immortall, whether there was a hell, whether there was a God: if all theſe atheiſticall opinions were buried in hell, yet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptations, and the helliſh corruptions of our own hearts would raiſe them up again; and therefore 'tis good to be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that we may ſtand faſt in <hi>this evil day,</hi> and having done all, <hi>to ſtand:</hi> Againſt this atheiſticall opinion, lay this down for a ſure foundation, ſurely there is <hi>another life beſides this life;</hi> and to ſtrengthen you therein, conſider theſe Arguments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Surely there is a God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paulus 3.</hi> Moriturus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiſſe fertur ſe jam expertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run veritaten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> trium quaeſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, de quibus in tota vita da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et; <hi>1.</hi> an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nimae ſint im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortales, <hi>2.</hi> an ſit inſernus: <hi>3.</hi> an ſit Deus, <hi>Gerrard,</hi> loc. com, de mort. p, 178.</note> 
               <hi>the heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament ſheweth forth his handy work:</hi> every creature pointeth us to the Creatour, and <hi>he that beleeveth not, is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of himſelf, and thou art left inexcuſable, O man:</hi> now if there be a God, there muſt needs be another life, wherein God will fulfill <hi>the good he hath promiſed,</hi> and execute <hi>the evil he hath threatned,</hi> for in this life there is <hi>arighteous man that periſheth in his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> and there is <hi>a wicked man that prolongeth his daies in his wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> Secondly, Conſider <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whom you heard not only to be the <hi>Son of man,</hi> but to be the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and the <hi>true Meſſiah,</hi> that great myſtery wherein God hath made known the riches of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for without controverſie <hi>great is the mystery of godlineſſe, Chriſt manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. 19.1. Eccleſ. 7.15. 1 Tim. 3.16.</note> a myſtery ſo much <hi>admired by the Apoſtles, ador'd by Angels, beleeved by Devils:</hi> if there be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, conſider</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> Firſt, What was the end of Chriſts incarnation? why did God become man, and he that was the <hi>mirrour of Angels,</hi> become the <hi>reproach of men?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.10.</note> was it not that he might bring <hi>many ſonne and daughters unto glory?</hi> and that glory, not in this life, for when he appeareth in another life,<note place="margin">Col. 3.4.2 Cor. 8.9.</note> then are the Saints to <hi>appear with him in glory:</hi> why became he poor, but that we <hi>through his poverty might be made rich.</hi> and obtain the riches of the glory of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance which <hi>is incorruptible, and undefiled,<note place="margin">1 Pet, 2, 3, 4.</note> and that paſſeth not away, reſerved in the higheſt heavens for them who are kept by the power of God through faith unto ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113005:16"/>
            <p>Secondly, What was the end of his bitter paſſion? why did be taſte <hi>death,</hi> who was the Lord <hi>of life;</hi> but that through death he might deſtroy him <hi>that had power over death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>that is the devil, and deliver them, who through the feare of death, were all their life time ſubject to bondage?</hi> and what deliverance from this death is imaginable? If the end of this life put an end to all our comforts, then the dangers of death are not <hi>abated,</hi> nor the feares of death a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit <hi>diminiſhed,</hi> but he was made perfect through ſuffering, that he might become <hi>the authour of eternall life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.9.</note> 
               <hi>to all that doe obey him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, What was the end of his <hi>reſurrection,</hi> but that his Saints might be <hi>quickned up together with him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.6. 1. Pet. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>and made to ſit in heavenly places together with him,</hi> and ſo obtain a lively hope, through the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, What was the end of Chriſts <hi>aſcenſion,</hi> but to prepare a place for his people? and if I go and prepare a place for you, ſaith Chriſt,<note place="margin">Joh. 14.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>I will come again and receive you,</hi> that where I am, there ye may be alſo.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, What is the end of his <hi>interceſſion,</hi> but that he may be able to <hi>ſave them to the utmoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>that come unto God through him?</hi> and how are they ſaved by him to the utmoſt, if there be not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life after this life? in this life the Saints <hi>are ſlain all the day long, and counted as ſheep unto the ſlaughter:</hi> therefore abhorre that blaſphemy, as once to imagine, that this <hi>great myſtery of piety,</hi> ſhould be a <hi>mystery of iniquity:</hi> if there were no other life expected then this, then as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the reſurrection, <hi>Chriſt is not riſen,</hi> ſo may I ſay then, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is neither <hi>borne,</hi> nor hath he ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor is he aſcended, nor ſitteth on the right hand of the <hi>Majeſty on high:</hi> deſpiſe not this glorious myſtery through unbeleife: for if he that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes his law, dyed without mercy, of how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall he be thought worthy, who treadeth under foot the Son of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.28, 29.</note> and treadeth the blood of the Covenant under his feet <hi>as an unholy thing,</hi> and doth deſpite to the ſpirit of grace?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> Conſider the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt: we have a <hi>ſure word of prophecy,</hi> to which we doe well to <hi>take heed, as to a light that ſhineth in a dark place;</hi> men may deceive, and be deceived, <hi>all fleſh is graſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23, 24.</note> and the goodlines thereof <hi>like the flower of the earth,</hi> but though men die, <hi>the Word of the Lord liveth and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113005:16"/>for ever,</hi> and though Heaven and Earth paſſe away,<note place="margin">Math. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>yet not one jet or title of this word ſhall paſſe away,</hi> now if you believe not that there is another life, then you make the Word of God to be a <hi>refuge of lies,</hi> and the holy Scripture is looked upon by you, as ſome <hi>impoſture,</hi> and read over the parts of the Covenant, and dare you imagine that his Commandements are irrationall?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider his Commandements, <hi>viz. Lay not up for your ſelves treaſures on Earth,</hi> which the moth corrupteth,<note place="margin">Math. 6.19. Joh. 6.27. Luk. 13.</note> and theeves break thorow and ſteale: <hi>labour not for the meat that periſheth, but for that which endureth to aternall life: ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate:</hi> and can theſe <hi>directions</hi> of the Lord of glory, be thought by you to be <hi>deluſions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the <hi>threats</hi> of the Covenant, doe you think them to be vaine affrightments? Chriſt ſaith, What ſhall it profit a man <hi>if he gaine the whole world, and loſe his own ſoul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16.16.</note> now if the ſoule be the temper of the body, and if there be no life but this, then the ſoule is loſt for ever: for every one muſt lay downe his life, there is no man living <hi>that ſhall not ſee death;</hi> Chriſt biddeth us feare <hi>him that killeth body and ſoul;</hi> why doe all the Scriptures tell us <hi>of devouring fires, everlasting burnings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.34. cap. 30.35.</note> that Tophet <hi>is prepared of old, the pile thereof is much wood,</hi> the breath of the Lord kindleth it, <hi>the worme never dyeth, and the fire never goeth out, but the ſmoke of the torment aſcendeth for ever and ever?</hi> doe you, or dare any one of you, when you heare the words of this curſe, bleſſe your ſelves in the imagination of your heart, and ſay, <hi>I ſhall have peace, though I adde drunkennes unto thirst?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 19.19.</note> be ſure though you deſpiſe this Word of the Lord, yet this word ſhall <hi>take hold of you,</hi> and all the curſes of this book <hi>ſhall lie upon you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. 1.6.</note> and the Lord ſhall blot out your name from under Heaven.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Look on the <hi>promiſes</hi> of this Covenant's and can any of you think thoſe promiſes which God counteth to be moſt precious, to be lies moſt pernitious? doth Chriſt uſe Stratagems to overreach his people? can you think the God of truth will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, who will not ſuffer <hi>any man to goe beyond,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>or defraud his brother, but will be an avenger of ſuch things?</hi> how often doth Chriſt engage himſelf by his promiſe,<note place="margin">Matth.'s 19.29.</note> that no man <hi>hath loſt fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or mother, houſes or lands for my name ſake,</hi> but ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive manifold in <hi>this life, and in the life to come eternall life?</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113005:17"/>how often doth he pronounce his Diſciples bleſt, when all men <hi>ſhall revile and perſecute them,</hi> and biddeth them rejoyce, <hi>and be exceeding glad</hi> in that day?<note place="margin">Math. 5.12, 13.</note> for though their troubles be great, yet their reward ſhall be greater <hi>in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, What doe you thinke of <hi>the graces</hi> of Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which are the <hi>fruits of the ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> as love, joy, peace? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If the eyes of our underſtanding <hi>be opened to know what</hi> is the hope <hi>of the calling,</hi> and the riches of the glory of the <hi>inheritance with the Saints</hi> in life, you cannot but confeſſe, that the worke of <hi>Converſion</hi> is greater then the worke of <hi>Creation,</hi> and the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding greatnes of his power towards them that beleeve, is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>mighty working of his power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>which he wrought in Chriſt,</hi> when he raiſed him from the dead: dare you without ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence and reluctance, entertaine a thought, <hi>that the reall grates of God</hi> are but the <hi>meere fancies of men?</hi> and that there is no diſtinction between good and evil, betwixt light and darknes? and involve your ſelves in that woe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Woe be unto them that call evil good, and good evil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, What doe you thinke of all the <hi>comforts</hi> of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? the joy of gods choſen,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.5.</note> to much <hi>begged by David,</hi> ſo much admired by the Apoſtle, that beleeving, <hi>the Saints rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8. Rom. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>and rejoyce in the hope of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God; and are ever looking for the bleſſed hope, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearing of the great God:</hi> the thoughts of the great day, when the ſun <hi>ſhall be darkned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.13.</note> and the moon <hi>turned into blood,</hi> rayſeth up their ſpirits higher, and Chriſt biddeth them lift up their <hi>heads,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.28.</note> 
               <hi>for their redemption then draweth neare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, What doe you think of the <hi>Children</hi> of this Covenant? the holy Prophets and Apoſtles, and Saints and Martyrs, who loved not <hi>their lives unto the death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but kept the word of Chriſts teſtimonie. <hi>Moſes</hi> was learned in all the wiſdome of the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, <hi>yet be refuſed to be called the ſonne in Law to: Pharaobs daughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>and choſe rather to ſuffer affliction with the children of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a moment,</hi> becauſe he had reſpect unto the <hi>recompence of reward. Paul</hi> brought up at the <hi>feet of Gamaliel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 20.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>counteth not his life deare unto him, that he may finiſh his courſe with joy,</hi> and of that cloud of witneſſes, how many of them were <hi>racked, tortured, and accepted not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113005:17"/>that they might obtaine a better reſurrection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.35.</note> Dare you condemne all the <hi>generation of the righteous,</hi> and ſoules of thoſe <hi>boly ones,</hi> that are now made perfect? if you imagine there is no other life beſides this, then you condemne, not onely the <hi>wiſest</hi> of men of <hi>folly,</hi> but the comforts, and the graces, and the threats, and the promiſes, and the commands, and directions of God, of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood: and that Atheiſtical foule that dares imagine the God of truth to be lyar, ſhall finde that God Almighty will give him his portion <hi>with lians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 21.8.</note> 
               <hi>and unbeleivers for ever in the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, Conſider the <hi>glorious Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.21. Math. 26.53. Heb. 12.22.</note> you have read of <hi>their ſtate</hi> and condition, that they <hi>are elect</hi> Angels; of their <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> that they are many <hi>legions,</hi> and an <hi>innumerable company of Angels,</hi> how they ſhall appeare with Chriſt at his comming in that great day, when he ſhall <hi>come with his mighty Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.31 Math. 22.30.</note> and how the happines of the Saints after death is, to be <hi>made like the Angels of God</hi> now <hi>conſider</hi> what is the great imployment of the Angels, to great in power, till that great day come? doth not the Scripture tell us that they wait over us? that they are <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Spirits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.14. Eſal. 34.7 Luk. 15.10. Matth. 11.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſont out for the good of them who ſhall be heires of Salvation?</hi> doe they not <hi>pitch their tonts about us?</hi> joy in our converſion? <hi>there is more joy in heaven among the Angels of God for the converſion of one ſinner, &amp;c. and they behold the face of God for us,</hi> and why is all this <hi>if there were no other life,</hi> then the joy of the Angels ſhould be founded upon fancies, and miſtakes, and their conſolation ſhould be a meer delnſion; there is litle <hi>reaſon</hi> to accoſet he <hi>best</hi> of men of <hi>madnes;</hi> but is madnes it ſelfe, for men to charge the elact Angels with folly.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Conſider the nature and the employment of thoſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpirits, Beeſzebub the old<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 12 9. 2 Pet. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>red Dragon</hi> and <hi>Serpent,</hi> called, <hi>the Davil and Satan, who deceiveth the world.</hi> Have you not read of their condition, how God hath bound them with <hi>chaines of darknes, and hath reſerved them for judgement?</hi> If ſo,<note place="margin">Quocumque vadunt geben. numſuam por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. <hi>Aq. 12.</hi> q. <hi>64.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmenta fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum ſecum ferunt inſtar ſebricitant is, qut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est's eburneis pona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſervorem evitare non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. <hi>Eſtrus,</hi> lib. <hi>2</hi> diſtin. <hi>6.13. Beda</hi> in Iacob. <hi>3. 2 Pet. 2.9, 10.22.</hi>
               </note> then there muſt be another world, at leaſt to them; and if to <hi>them,</hi> then <hi>to us:</hi> for if God ſpared not the Angels that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but caſt them <hi>down, to Hell,</hi> that where ever they goe <hi>they carry their chaine and their holl with them:</hi> ſurely then God knoweth how to reſerve the <hi>unjust for the day of Judgement; cherfly thoſe that walk af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113005:18"/>the fleſh, ſpeaking evil of things they know not, ſporting themſelves with their own deceiving; thoſe men ſhall utterly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in their own corruptions.</hi> Have ye not heard of the horrour that overwhelmeth them, that they are forced, though they <hi>reſiſt</hi> God, to beleeve that which they <hi>approve</hi> not, and <hi>to tremble</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wrath they cannot avoid? But eſpecially thinke of that imployment, how they walke <hi>thorow drie places,</hi> fretting and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, running too and fro, <hi>and compaſſing the Earth;</hi> how Satan entred <hi>into the heart of Judas</hi> to betray his Maſter,<note place="margin">Jam. 2.19. Math. 11.43. Job. 1.7. Luk. 22.3. Act. 5.3.</note> filled <hi>Ananias and Saphira to lye againſt</hi> the Holy Ghoſt. What paines they take to leade away the ſoules of poor men and women captive? If there were not another <hi>life beſides, this,</hi> and if the ſoule were not immortall, why is it that thoſe ſpirits goe about <hi>continually ſeeking whom they may devoure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> and never ceaſe to accuſe God to us, <hi>and day and night to accuſe the Saints unto God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>6</label> Sixthly, Adde to all theſe, the conſideration <hi>of witches and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards:</hi> you haue heard, how <hi>Saul</hi> ſought <hi>to the witch of Endor,</hi> how that <hi>witch had familiar ſpirits at her command,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> how <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh made his ſonnes paſſe thorow the fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>uſed inchaniments, dealt with familiar ſpirits and wizards,</hi> how this ſinne did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound amongſt the Canaanites of old, how ſtrictly God forbad the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that there ſhould not be amongſt them any one <hi>that uſed divination, or an inchanter, or a witch, or a charmer, or a conſultour with familiar spirits, or a wizard,</hi> or a Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer,<note place="margin">Deut. 18.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>for all that doe thoſe things are an abomination to the Lord,</hi> and for all theſe abominations <hi>did the Lord drive them out from before them.</hi> How did Satan deceive the Nations by the Oracle of <hi>Delphos?</hi> how hath this ſinne raigned in all ages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Caldeans, the Jewes, and Gentiles? which things are ſo evident, as none can deny them: and can any one imagine that Satan would be ſo <hi>ſollicitous</hi> to ſeduce, <hi>ready to captivate,</hi> ſo <hi>obſequious</hi> for a time to become a drudge and a vaſſall to the <hi>poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> of men, and <hi>ſillieſt</hi> of women, that he may winne their ſoules, if there were no other life then this life? To this adjoyne the art of Conjuring; which though abominable beyond expreſſion, yet it is ſo notorious in all places, and in all ages, that it is beyond the deniall of any, who hath not ſunke himſelfe below his <hi>ſpecies,</hi> who,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113005:18"/>leſt his luſt ſhould be diſquieted, and his ſoul tormented before his time, hath ſold himſelfe over to be a ſlave to unbeleife, and is reſolved to ſhut his eyes againſt the light of Scripture, and againſt the light of Nature, and to cloſe his eares againſt all the loud cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the heart within, and experiences without: and what ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments can convince that ſoule, which hath made a Covenant with death, <hi>and is at agreement with Hell,</hi> that is reſolved, what ever is ſaid to perſwade him, yet he will not be perſwaded? and though one, or ten thouſand ſhould riſe from the dead, that ſoule will not be <hi>perſwaded,</hi> leſt that his luſts ſhould be <hi>moleſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>7</label> Seventhly, Conſider the naturall conſcience that is in all men: <hi>their thoughts one while accuſing &amp; excuſing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> what inward gripes and ſecret terrours, ſtill poor mad wretches ſuffer themſelves to be ſo baffled and maſter'd with their luſts, that at length they joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their luſts, to <hi>baffle</hi> and get the victory over their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, that being <hi>paſt feeling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4 19.</note> 
               <hi>they may commit ſin with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines:</hi> yet when they have done all, they finde it difficult to keep down theſe ſparks, and to ſuppreſſe theſe flaſhes that are ever riſing up. If this be rightly weighed, it may be reputed one Argument, that the thoughts of another life, of another day of account, are written on the hearts of all men, and that the imagination to the contrary, is rather an <hi>option</hi> then an <hi>opinion;</hi> rather an intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what is <hi>deſired</hi> by them, then <hi>beleived</hi> of them; eſpecially if you in the naturall conſcience conſider theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The inquiſitions about immortality, all queſtions, doubts, debates upon this ſubject argue the ſoul to be immortall; for it is only a principle of immortality that maketh man diſpute whether the ſoule be immortall; for as none can diſtinguiſh betwixt ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and irrationall, but he that is rationall,<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Morn.</hi> de veritate rel. Cir. p. <hi>293.</hi>
               </note> for he that denyeth man to be rationall, by doubting <hi>of it,</hi> and diſputing <hi>against it,</hi> in thoſe acts proveth himſelfe to be rationall, which his words ſeem to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: ſo none can diſpute or diſtinguiſh betwixt mortall and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, but only he that is immortall: and theſe thoughts of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality are not only in ſome men of ſome tempets, but upon the hearts of all the ſonnes of men.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider the affectation of a kinde of immortality in the worſt of men, who have taken great paines to gull themſelves into an opinion that the ſoule is mortall. What <hi>monuments,</hi> what
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113005:19"/>
               <hi>pillars</hi> have they erected?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 49.11. Ph. Morn.</hi> ibid. p. <hi>202.</hi> Vulgus deſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis parentat, &amp; quidem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi ſimo officio, &amp; quos negat ſentire quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam etiam deſiderare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Tertul.</hi> de re ur carnis</note> how have they called their land <hi>after their own names?</hi> tis obſerved by him that was an honour to the Nobility, that <hi>Epicurus</hi> himſelfe, who denyed immortality in his life, yet he appointed <hi>at his death</hi> a great ſumme of money to be yearly payed, that there might be an annuall commemoration of the day <hi>of his birth;</hi> and to what purpoſe is this, if when he lived like a beaſt, he muſt die like a hogg? if nothing be immortall, why when immortality was ſo groundleſly denied, is this kinde of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality ſo ſillily deſired?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Think of the unſatisfiednes of the minde in things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and you ſhall finde the ſoule in a continued purſuit, reaching after ſomething that is infinite; other creatures have here their home, have their minde ſatisfied; but the workings of the ſoule are ſtill for future; ſome way forgetting, by a naturall inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the things behinde, and ſtretching forward to finde out that in <hi>things future</hi> which it hath ſought in <hi>things paſt,</hi> and ever was diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: now the operations of all creatures follow their eſſence; this tendency of the minde to the future, argueth the ſoule to be <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> in the way, and not in its own countrey, and that we are not <hi>yet at home,</hi> that this life is but a paſſage to another.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Conſider the confeſſions of adverſaries at <hi>their death,</hi> who have denyed this truth in <hi>their life. Belſhazzar</hi> in the height of his jollity, when the hand-writing apeared on the wall, <hi>his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was changed, and his thoughts troubled, ſo that the joints of his loynes were looſed, and his knees ſmote one againſt the other, Dan.</hi> 5.6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>8</label> Eightly,<note place="margin">Phil. Motn. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</note> To this might be added the providence of God: if we beleeve <hi>Plutarch</hi> and other heathen authours, this diſpute is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for Gods providence and the ſoules immortality are ſo united together, that he that denies the one, deſtroyeth the other; why did God make this world ſo full of beauty, but that ſome ſhould behold the Creatour in it? why ſhould man contemplate the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour</hi> in the <hi>Creature,</hi> but to adore him? why ſhould man above all ſublunary creatures adore him, if man above the reſt of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had no hope in him? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. he that <hi>commeth to adore God, must beleeve that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that ſeek him;</hi> thoſe rewards are not diſpenſed here, therefore are reſerved for <hi>a life hereafter:</hi> why hath God given ſo many gifts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113005:19"/>unto man, which perplex him in <hi>this life;</hi> and fills his minde with thoſe dſiquietments, that all the bruriſh creatures are freed from? in regard of theſe man ſhould be <hi>worſe</hi> then a <hi>beaſt</hi> in his <hi>life,</hi> if not better then a beaſt <hi>at his death;</hi> and we may ſay of men, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to other creatures, as the Apoſtle ſaith of Chriſtians, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to other men, If man had only hope in this life, man of all creatures would be moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>9</label> Ninthly, To thoſe might be added all the arguments that prove the <hi>day of judgement, that God hath appointed a time, wherein he will judge the world in righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.31.</note> by that man whom he hath ordained, whereof he hath given aſſurance to all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>10</label> Adde to all theſe the arguments in this chapter, whereby the Apoſtle proves <hi>the reſurrection of the body,</hi> and anſwers all obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the contrary, with all thoſe Scriptures that tell us plainely that Jeſus ſhall come in <hi>his glory, and all his holy Angels with him; before him ſhall be gathered all nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.31, 32. 1 Theſ. 4.16. Joh. 5 28.28.</note> and he ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them one from another, <hi>as a ſhepherd doth the ſheep from the Goats,</hi> and it is but a little time before the Lord ſhall <hi>deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the voice of an Arch-angel, with the trump of God, and then the dead ſhall riſe;</hi> and the day is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>when all that are in their graves ſhall heare the voice of the Sonne of man, and they that have done good, ſhall come to the reſurrection of life, and they that have done evil, to the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of condemnation.</hi> I will couclude with that of <hi>Chryſiſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, How. <hi>5.</hi> in Act. cap. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Anime cauſâ eſt omnis reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro, <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de utilit, tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi c. <hi>7.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de jamolim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter philoſophos ijdem omnem religionem ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſtuletunt, qui anima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> marta lei dixerunt. <hi>Eſtius,</hi> l. <hi>4</hi> diſt. <hi>43. Iſa. 7 9. And Errour confuted.</hi>
               </note> that the <hi>Devils great deſigne hath been ever to perſwade man,</hi> that the nature of man differed little from the nature of beaſts; and when he had drawn any of the ſonnes of men <hi>into this flrange ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity,</hi> to diſpute themſelves out of the thoughts of their own immortality, he hath ſo farre prevailed to blinde many of them, that after they have affirmed the nature of the immortall ſoule to be mortall, they have gone about to prove the nature of beaſts, <hi>which is void of reaſon, to be rationall;</hi> whileſt theſe great truths are queſtioned, the ſoule neglects to be ſanctified; <hi>all piety is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the thoughts of immortality;</hi> and it is obſerved among all the Philoſophers, that thoſe deſtroyed all Religion that held the ſoule to be mortall. Till this great truth be ſetled upon the hearts of men, they lye open to all temptations, and ſuffer themſelves
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113005:20"/>to beled away with all corruption. If you <hi>beleive</hi> not this, you can never <hi>be establiſhed,</hi> therefore be not faithleſſe, but belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is a ſecond errour of the <hi>Semi-atheiſts,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that there is a day of judgement and a reſurrection; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that the Scriptures hold out, <hi>that the ſoul is diſtinct from the body, or that the ſoul hath any abiding after the body is diſſolved, but ſleeps till the day of reſurrection;</hi> I could be willing to bury this errour in everlaſting ſilence, but that ſome have raiſed it from the embers, and in theſe times with <hi>unſufferable boldnes,</hi> under the notion of new light,<note place="margin">Vid <hi>Auguſt.</hi> haereſ. <hi>83.</hi> Husc errorem <hi>Mahomet</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit in ſu, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cborano, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can;, &amp; corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra &amp; animas adextremun, judicium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrecturas. <hi>Eſtius</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>43</hi> Anno Don. <hi>1568.</hi> Theſes Craco viá impreſſas per Polontam divulgarunt, quarum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m poſt morrem mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, &amp;c. <hi>Soule is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the body.</hi> Vid. <hi>Aquin.</hi> contragent. l. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>267. Heb. 12.9. Eccleſ. 11.5. Pſal. 22 9.</hi>
               </note> have uſhered in this im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of darknes. This errour began to vent it ſelfe by the heathen, afterwards to poiſon <hi>Tatianus</hi> after the time of <hi>Juſtine Martyr,</hi> and after him ſome other Chriſtians in <hi>Arabia;</hi> yet in thoſe dayes this errour was ſo ſufficiently refuted, that it ſeemed for many ages dead and buried, till <hi>Mahomet</hi> that falſe Prophet, who having a carnall minde, and ſavouring nothing of the ſpirit, dreamed only of corporall paines and pleaſures that men ſhould have after the reſurrection; and among Chriſtians it appeared little, till Satan, to blemiſh that glo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reformation, in the dayes of <hi>Luther,</hi> ſtirred up ſome Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts in <hi>Polonia,</hi> and ſince, the Socinians and Libertines, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive this moncter. I have not time thorowly to diſcover the root of this poiſon: only give me leave to leade you by the hand to ſome ſoveraigne <hi>Antidotes,</hi> as ſtrong <hi>preſervatives</hi> againſt this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>To this end conſider theſe two poſitions:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Scripture cleerly holdeth out, <hi>that the ſoul is diſtinct from the body.</hi> I paſſe over the arguments that <hi>learned men</hi> bring from the light of nature to confute this errour. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what the God of truth hath revealed, and you ſhall finde that the Scripture telleth us cleerly, that though the ſoul be <hi>united to the body,</hi> yet it is <hi>diſtinct from the body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in its <hi>riſe, Gen.</hi> 2.7. we have had <hi>the fathers of our fleſh, and have been obedient to them;</hi> how much more to <hi>the father of ſpirits, and live?</hi> though God <hi>frame our bodies, cauſe our bones to grow in our Mothers wombe, take us out of our Mothers bellyt</hi> yet he uſeth our naturall parents as inſtruments of our body, but it is Gods great prerogative to be the immediate <hi>father of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Iſa.</hi> 57, 16.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113005:20"/>
            <p>Secondly, It is diſtinct in its <hi>naturall operation, is:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt the ſoule <hi>groweth moſt</hi> when the <hi>body groweth least:</hi> there are diſtinct periods of time, beyond which it is impoſſible to adde either a cubit, or a haires breadth <hi>to ones ſtature:</hi> but the ſoule is ever growing forward <hi>to its perfection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 32.7.</note> 
               <hi>and multitudes of years,</hi> though full of weaknes, <hi>yet they utter wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſoule is often <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> when the body is <hi>weakeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Cor.</hi> Anima regit corpus, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnat paſſioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexionem ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quntur. <hi>Aquin.</hi> Contra Gent. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> dying Chriſtians have manifeſted the higheſt <hi>excellency</hi> under <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily infirmities:</hi> when there hath been the leaſt of the <hi>life of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> there hath been moſt tranſcendent glorious expreſſions of the <hi>life of grace:</hi> and for this cauſe they <hi>fainted not,</hi> finding by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that when <hi>their outward man decayed, their inward man was renewed day by day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The ſoule is not the temper of the body, becauſe it rules the temper, and diſtempers of body.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, They are diſtinct in <hi>ſupernaturall conſolations,</hi> when all joy of the body hath been darkned, the ſupernaturall joyes of the ſoule have been enlarged: when the bodies of Martyrs have been on the rack, under torturings, how have their ſoules been fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with inward triumphings, embracing the <hi>burning flames</hi> like <hi>beds of reſes,</hi> and have endured all the dreadfull things that men could inflict, to the admiration of their enemies, and the convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of many of their beholders? as <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, They are diſtinct in their <hi>unnaturall pollutions,</hi> there are ſpirituall wickedneſſes and malignities, as well as bodily, and we are bid to cleanſe our ſelves from <hi>all filt hineſſe of fleſh and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1. 1 Pet. 2.11.</note> and to abſtaite <hi>fromall fleſhly lusts, which warte againſt the ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>5</label> Fifthly, They are diſtinct in regard of the <hi>oppoſite duties</hi> requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of man, in demeaning himſelfe to <hi>his body</hi> and to <hi>his ſoule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6.25.</note> Chriſt hath commanded us to <hi>take no thought for the body,</hi> but did he ever command us to take no thought for the ſoule? are not his commands quite contrary, <hi>viz. above all things looke to thy ſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dent. 4.9. 2 Pet. 1.10. Phil. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>and keep thy ſoule diligently, and give all diligence to make your calling and election ſure: and work out your ſalvation with feare and trembling;</hi> now if God require thoſe acts to be performed to the ſoule, which are abſolutely forbidden to the body: then the ſoule muſt needs be diſtinct from the body.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113005:21"/>
            <p>Sixthly, They are diſtinct at <hi>the time of diſſolution,</hi> when they part one from the other, when the Servants of God have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended their bodies to the ground, how have their ſoules rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to goe out of this Tabernacle? as <hi>Hilario<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Polycarp: Stephen</hi> when his body was ſtoned, ſeeth <hi>Heaven opened, and cryed, Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 7.56. and 59.</note> if the ſoule therefore be distinct from the body, in the <hi>riſe,</hi> in the <hi>working, in its conſolation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, in its duties, in its pollutions, and in the ſtate after death,</hi> than to <hi>confound</hi> the ſoule with the body is as great an errour, as to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found life with death,</hi> and light with darknes. But eſpecially conſider that all thoſe arguments that prove the ſoule to exiſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the body, doe anſwerably confute that Errour, that the ſoule is but <hi>the temper of the body,</hi> therefore conſider the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Poſition.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>2</label> The Scripture expreſſely teacheth us, that the ſoule is not onely diſtinct from the body:<note place="margin">Sour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> immmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, and doth not ſleep till the day of the reſurrection.</note> but that the ſoule liveth, when ſeparate from the body, and that it is but a fancy of inconſiderate ſpirits, to dreame that the ſoule ſleepeth till the day of reſurrection: for the cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ering of this truth conſider three arguments.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> Firſt, Conſider the ſoules of the Saints, and you ſhall finde that their ſoules doe not ſleep with their bodies: but that the Scripture, ſpeaketh expreſlely, that in the day of their death,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, they are gathered <hi>to their fathers,</hi> ſo it is ſaid of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 25.8. now if <hi>Abraham</hi> was gathered to his fathers, this muſt be in his ſoule, for in his body there was no ſuch gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his progenitors being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of the <hi>Chalde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> body was interred in the cave of <hi>Machpelah before Mamre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.9.</note> 
               <hi>in the land of Cannan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.43.</note> Chriſt promiſed the poor penitent thiefe on the croſſe, this day ſhalt thou <hi>be with me in Paradiſe,</hi> there are ſome to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void this Scripture, would divide the words thus, I ſay unto thee this day, and make a ſtop there; referring the word, this day to <hi>the perſon promiſing,</hi> and not to the bleſſing <hi>promiſed;</hi> to which I anſwer, that firſt, to alter comma's &amp; ſtops, againſt all received co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, is a high preſumption, which, if tolerated, how will the ſenſe of Scripture be wreſted by wanton wits <hi>to their own perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.16. Luk. 23.41.</note> the Context ſufficiently confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth this gloſſe, Chriſt anſwereth the deſire of the poor penitent thiefe, his requeſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113005:21"/>is, <hi>Lord, remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdome:</hi> but Chriſt immediately that day entred into his kindome; now in Chriſts anſwer, none can imagine the words to be a denyall: and if there be a granting his petition, then to interpret the words, that ſome thouſand yeares after, <hi>viz.</hi> at the day of the reſurrection the thiefe ſhould be remembred; is to abuſe the faith of this poor penitent, to ſtraiten Chriſts bounty, and to wreſt the words againſt their naturall ſenſe, that ſay expreſſely, this day, Chriſt <hi>hodiè</hi> muſt anſwer to the penitents <hi>quando,</hi> and if in Paradiſe, then ſurely not in the grave, nor in any part of the Earth, as that Paradiſe in the day of the Creation full of trees and herbs; for Chriſt entred into the Heavenly Paradiſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.2.4.</note> and when <hi>Paul</hi> was wrapt up into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, he telleth us it was <hi>the third Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, You have read how <hi>Lazarus</hi> after his death was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed into <hi>Abrahams boſome,</hi> and that place,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.22.</hi> Non quietis l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, ſed aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis ſinum, <hi>Aug. Calvin.</hi>
               </note> not a place of quiet <hi>tranquillity,</hi> but the boſome <hi>of Eternall felicity:</hi> and though ſome diſpute whether the relation be a hiſtory, or a parable, yet how ever, though you ſuppoſe it to be parabolicall, yet a parable is the <hi>ſimilitude of ſome reall truth,</hi> and this Parable cannot ſignify what ſhall be done after the day of judgement, but plainely point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to a ſtate the ſoules are in, before that day, for after the day of judgement, what man can ſay as <hi>Dives</hi> did,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.28, 29. 1 Cor. 15.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>I have three bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren upon the Earth?</hi> or how could <hi>Abraham</hi> returne that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, they have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for after that day all ordinances ſhall ceaſe, <hi>and God ſhall be all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Conſider the <hi>Saints deſire of diſſolution</hi> is upon this perſwaſion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> If <hi>Paul</hi> had imagined his ſoule ſhould have ſlept till the day of reſurrection, it had been weaknes and madneſſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire diſſolution for this end, to be with Chriſt; for if this ſhould be true, then <hi>Paul</hi> had more of Chriſt in life, (for then Chriſt lived in him,) then poſſibly he could attaine to after death, if the ſoule ſhould ſleep till the day of reſurrection.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Conſider the Saints <hi>confidence upon their departure</hi> from Earth to enjoy a glorious life in Heaven; we know that when this earthly tabernacle <hi>the body is diſſolved, we have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eternall in the Heavens,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. ſurely if the ſoul ſleep till the day of reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113005:22"/>they ſhould not have ſaid, when this <hi>houſe is diſſolved,</hi> but when this body is <hi>raiſed,</hi> and this tabernacle <hi>restored:</hi> when they deſire to part with the body, this were out of love to their ſoules, not out of want of love to their bodies; for <hi>Paul</hi> could have wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>mortality to be ſwallowed up of life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>(i.e.)</hi> that the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body might have gone to life with the immortall ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, The Scripture ſpeaketh expreſſely, that all the <hi>preſence</hi> the Saints have with Chriſt, while the ſoule is in the body, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a <hi>meer abſence,</hi> in compariſon of that neernes of preſence unto Chriſt, which they ſhall enjoy when they are <hi>abſent from the body:</hi> for the Apoſtle ſpeaketh this confidently, knowing <hi>that whilſt we are at home in the body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.6, 8.</note> 
               <hi>we are abſent from the Lord:</hi> and we are confident and willing rather to be abſent from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and to be preſent with the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seventhly, Conſider that the ſoule upon its ſeparation from the body,<note place="margin">Heb 12.23.</note> is ſo farre from being aboliſhed, that it is <hi>perfected,</hi> and the Saints departed this life, are by the holy Ghoſt ſtiled the <hi>ſoules of juſt men made perfect:</hi> to this I might adde many more argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as that the <hi>happines of the Saints is in a perpetual progreſſe. Phil.</hi> 1.6, <hi>that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> they have with Chriſt, is <hi>inſeparable</hi> beyond the power of death, what ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>That the happines of the Saints is Eternall, Joh.</hi> 5.44. &amp; 6.40,<note place="margin">Rev. 6.9, 10.</note> 42. that the ſoules under the altar, cry <hi>for the reſurrection of the body,</hi> that the <hi>counſell</hi> of Chriſt to his hearers was upon this foundation, <hi>make you friends of this unrighteous mammon,</hi> that when they faile, they may receive you into everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting manſions, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.9. but all theſe things faile us at the day of death, therefore at that day the promiſe is to be received into everlaſting manſions; thus you ſee the truth evidenced from the ſoules of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Conſider the ſoules of wicked men, that at the hour of death <hi>they are not aboliſhed:</hi> God telleth us,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, That they goe to <hi>their own place,</hi> ſo tis ſaid of <hi>Judas,</hi> who fell <hi>by tranſgreſſion:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.18, 25.</note> now that place is not the grave, for the grave is not his owne place, that is the <hi>common way of all fleſh,</hi> and that place where all meet together.<note place="margin">Job. 3.18, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Judas</hi> his place was the ſtate and degree of torment, that his ſinne and <hi>Gods juſtice</hi> inflicted on him.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113005:22"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, The ſoules of them of the old world <hi>are now in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Chriſt in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> by his eternall ſpirit, preached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>whoſe ſpirits are now in priſon:</hi> the grave cannot be the priſon to diſtinguiſh the juſt from the unjuſt: that being common to the obedient, as well as to the diſobedient, 2 <hi>Pet,</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, They are ſaid to be in <hi>the place of torment; Dives,</hi> when his body was buried, is ſaid to have his ſoule in torment, and he beggeth of <hi>Abraham, ſend to my brethren, that they come not to this place of torment:</hi> many prove this Scripture to be hiſtoricall, but ſuppoſe it in part to be a parable, as ſome expreſſions are gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all to be <hi>parabolicall,</hi> as the tongue of <hi>Dives,</hi> and the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> yet this Parable muſt be a reſemblance of ſome truth, which is in <hi>rerum naturâ,</hi> and muſt intimate ſomething paſt, not future after the reſurrection, as was proved for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Tis ſaid of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> that they now ſuffer <hi>the vengeance of eternall fire;</hi> it cannot be meant of their bodies,<note place="margin">Jud. ver. 7.</note> for they are burnt by fire to aſhes, nor of that materiall fire that fell upon their Cities, for that many ages ſince was quenched; but of their ſoules, which are under the eternall wrath of God, where the worme <hi>never dieth, and where the fire is never quenched.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 9.44.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what the Scripture ſaith of the <hi>ſoules of all men in generall,</hi> whether juſt or unjuſt, whether they feare God or feare him not.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, That the ſoule man is not capable of corruption; <note place="margin">Matth. 10.28.</note> Chriſt biddeth us not feare <hi>him that killeth the body, and cannot kill the ſoule;</hi> now if the ſoule was but the temper of the body, then whoſoever killeth the body, ſhould by the ſame act kill the ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, When the ſoule and body part, the Scripture telleth us they goe to diſtinct places: who conſidereth the ſpirit of a beaſt that goeth downward, <hi>and the ſpirit of a man that gooth upward?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> yet though man doe not conſider it, the God of truth aſſerteth it,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> when man dieth, then ſhall the duſt <hi>returne to the Earth as it was, and the spirit to God that gave it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the ſoule ſhould ſleep till the reſurrection,<note place="margin">Corpus non ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it poſt ſeceſsum, manet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>igitur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> magit anima. <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> then the ſoule ſhould <hi>be as mortall</hi> as the body, for the body is not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſolved into a <hi>non entity:</hi> when it is parted from the ſoule: and if the body be not <hi>aboliſhed,</hi> can any one thinke the ſoule to be <hi>anihilated?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113005:23"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, If this ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thou the reſurrection of the ſoule ſhould be as needfull to be <hi>reveal'd</hi> in Scripture, and would prove as difficult to men to beleeve, as the reſurrection of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; but about the reſurrection of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcripture is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſilent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, The expreſſion of death by the Holy ghoſt <hi>is a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet 1 14.</note> 
               <hi>putting off this tabernacle</hi> and it is a ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ake to take the houſe for the inhabitant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, I cannot rockon the world of abſurdities which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this great errour, that it, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gap</hi> to the overthrow of all the thoughts of Eternity, for if arguments from nature can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile to delude the ſoule ſo farre, as to thinke the ſoule is aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at death, what arguments can prevaile with a carnall heart to perſwade it, that the body ſhall be raiſed after death; the voice of nature cryed aloud amongſt the heathen, <hi>that the ſoules of man were immortall,</hi> and that there was a different ſtate of the ſoules of juſt men, and unjuſt, after death: the <hi>Elizian</hi> fields, full of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for the one ſort, and the <hi>Tartarean</hi> darknes full of horrour, for the other: tis an ancient obſervation, that almoſt all Philoſophers, all Hereticks <hi>confeſſed the ſoule to be immortall, and though they did not much deſire it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Animae ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credo tractatu carere: omnes fere baeretici e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quoquo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do volunt, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non nega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Tertul.</hi> de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. Carnis.</note> yet they were not able to deny it; but the reſurrection from the dead was by few of them diſcerned, ſcarce by any of them acknowledged: beſides this errour is <hi>destructive to all religion;</hi> our corrupt natures are full of the ſeeds of Atheiſme: we need all religion to eradicate them; but nothing to foment them: thoughts of Epicuriſme ſinke deep, <hi>to count the fruition of carnall</hi> pleaſures <hi>the greateſt good:</hi> how many thouſand ſoules have miſcarryed upon this rock? who from hence have turned to be lovers <hi>of pleaſures more then of God:</hi> to preſerve your ſoules from this infection,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.4.</hi> Vid. <hi>Tertul. Lactan.</hi> &amp;c. Diſcede ab Ethnico, haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, quid ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eno uteris cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peo, ſi ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolo ornatus es. <hi>Tertul.</hi> de reſur.</note> I have been thus large in proving this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I ſhould proceed to confute the arguments brought to the contrary, but the time preventeth me: onely in briefe, their argn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are either drawne from corrupt nature, which are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly anſwered by the <hi>fathers</hi> in their diſputes againſt the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and they wondred that hereticall Chriſtians, that enjoyed <hi>the light of Scripture, ſhould borrow any arguments from Galen,</hi> and the reſt of the heathen that ſat in darkneſſe, and in the valley <hi>of the ſhadow of death;</hi> let Heathens turne to Chriſtians to aſſert this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113005:23"/>truth, but never let Chriſtians ſo ſarre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tatiſe to Heathens, as to <hi>aſſert their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orrours:</hi> or elſe their objections and ſeeming argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are taken from miſtaken Scripture: I have ſcarcely time to relate them, much leſſe to refute them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Some object and ſay, Did not God threaten <hi>Adam, In the day thou eaſeſt thereof, thou ſhalt die;</hi> and if he died,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> then the whole man did die, for the body is not the man without the ſoul, and therefore reaſon, that immortall <hi>Adam,</hi> muſt be made mortall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To this I anſwer; 1. That the death which God did threaten, was not only naturall, but <hi>spirituall</hi> and <hi>eternall;</hi> and ſpirituall and eternall death may be upon the ſoul, when the body periſheth: the Angels that fell from their firſt ſtanding, are <hi>under death,</hi> yet their being is <hi>not aboliſhed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 20.10, 14.</note> and after the day of judgement, the wicked ſhall be caſt into hell, the ſecond death, yet they ſhall never be reduced to a <hi>non entitie,</hi> for the ſmoake of <hi>their torment aſcondeth for over.</hi> If any ſay,<note place="margin">Rev. 14.11.</note> Why is the whole man ſaid to die, if the ſoul liveth when the body is deſtroyed? Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That whatſoever belongeth to any part of any whole,<note place="margin">Quicquid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit parti, qua pars, convenit toti ſecundum illam partem.</note> may be truly aſſcribed to the whole, according to that part. Man ſeeth, yet the whole body is not an eye, for then where was the eare? but the whole <hi>light of the body is the eye.</hi> Chriſt was born, put to death, buried, and this is ſaid of whole Chriſt, but this is only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the <hi>humane</hi> nature, for the God-head is immortall,<note place="margin">2. pet. 3.18.</note> and therefore he was <hi>put to</hi> death in the fleſh only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But they ſay, When men are dead, the Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaith, that they <hi>cannot praiſe God;</hi> Pſal. 6.5. and 88.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> I anſwer; the dead, <hi>qui tales,</hi> ſo farre as they are dead, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not praiſe God;<note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> the body that lieth in the grave <hi>reſteth from its labour,</hi> yet this doth not exclude the realiy of the act, but the manner of the performance; and ſo ſaith <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> they ſhall not praiſe thee as I do this day,<note place="margin">Iſa. 38.19.</note> the <hi>father to the children ſhall make known Gods truth.</hi> 1. Though they cannot do it for anothers <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,</hi> yet they can do it for their <hi>own conſolation;</hi> and theſe ſouls that are with the Lord, <hi>they follow the Lamb where ever he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> and have their <hi>hallelujahs</hi> continually in their mouth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. and bleſſed be they <hi>that dwell in God preſence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.4.</note> 
               <hi>they will be alwaies praiſing him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> God is ſaid only to have immortalitie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:113005:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> God alone is immortall, <hi>à parte ante,</hi> from all eternity; he alone is independently, unchangeably, infinitly immortall; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible 'tis for any creature, or all the creatures to <hi>anihilate God:</hi> 'tis an eaſie thing with God to anihilate any of his creatures, he alone is <hi>the authour and continuer of immortality.</hi> But I dare not in this point preſume to detain you any longer; what ever fleſh and bloud may ſuggeſt, or carnall reaſon object, let your ſouls everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly dwell upon this ſtrong foundation, beleeving that there is <hi>another life beſides this life.</hi> There are many other Uſes of this Doctrin, to perſwade you not only to beleeve this truth ſtedfaſtly, but to bleſſe God for it abundantly.</p>
            <p>That your ſouls doe not die with your bodie, herein triumph, that death hath no power of abſolute <hi>deſtroying,</hi> but only of <hi>chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and that change to your ſouls (if you be in Chriſt) is unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably for the better. Be you therefore intreated all the daies of your life and appointed <hi>time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>to wait till your change come:</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem this truth as one part of the oracles of God moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and one of the greateſt remedies <hi>against</hi> all <hi>future</hi> fears, and <hi>preſent miſeries,</hi> that though death deſtroy your bodie, yet your hope may be in the rock of eternity, that you may ſay, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth here, If we had <hi>hopes only in Christ in this life,</hi> we were of <hi>all most miſerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As you have heard the extent of this hope,<note place="margin">The <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> part</note> ſo conſider the <hi>ground of this extent,</hi> here expreſt by the Apoſtle, drawn from an abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, that the beſt of men otherwiſe ſhould be moſt <hi>miſerables</hi> which is an abſurdity ſo groſſe which the light of nature cannot but abhorre; and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> counts it needleſſe to uſe any other arguments to refute: hence obſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> If all the <hi>good that the ſoul expects from Chriſt ſhould be limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this life, then the best Chriſtians ſhould be most miſerable.</hi> And if ſo, then God the beſt maſter ſhould be the worſt; and the children of wiſdome ſhould be the ſons of folly; then might the Epicure and Atheiſt bleſſe themſelves in their own luſts, call the <hi>proud happy,</hi> and ſay, it is <hi>in vain to ſerve the Lord,</hi> and what profit is it,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.14, 15.</note> that <hi>any have kept his ordinances, and walked mournfully</hi> before the Lord of hoſts?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Why? may ſome ſay, if there be an end of all good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to all men at the end of this life, yet wherein are the Saints
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113005:24"/>worſe then others? Is not their condition <hi>at leaſt equall</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of other men? though there ſhould be no heaven to crown the righteous, and no heli to torment the wicked, yet is it not an excellency in it ſelf to chooſe good and refuſe evil? Should not vertue be loved for it ſelf? Can there be any greater reward to goodneſſe, then goodneſſe it ſelf? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, however it be a pleaſant thing in it ſelf, to <hi>praiſe the Lord with joyfull lips,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 36.8. 1 Pet. 2.3.</note> yet after that the ſoul hath <hi>drunk of the Rivers of Gods pleaſures, taſted that the Lord is gracious,</hi> made their <hi>boast</hi> of God, and <hi>triumphed in the hope</hi> of the glory of Chriſt, then for the ſeul to goe under a dark cloud, and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly to be cut off from thoſe raviſhing enjoyments: this would make the Saints in many reſpects more miſerable then other men.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Resp. </seg>1</label> The comforts of Chriſtians, as they are Chriſtians, in things of this <hi>life are fewer:</hi> God of ſet purpoſe calls their hearts off from the creature, commands them to forſake <hi>Father and Mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.37. Mark 8.34. Gen. 12.1. Heb. 11.24.</note> 
               <hi>houſe and land, for his Name ſake,</hi> bids <hi>them deny themſelves, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> muſt forſake <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r of the Chaldees: Moſes</hi> muſt <hi>refuſe to be called the ſon of Pharaohs daughter:</hi> The Diſciples leave all to follow Chriſt; and they are promiſed,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.28.</note> that when the ſon of man ſhall ſit in the throne <hi>of his glory, that then they</hi> alſo ſhall <hi>ſit upon thrones, judging the twelve</hi> Tribes of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Resp. </seg>2</label> The diſcomforts and afflictions that the Saints endure for Chriſt are heavier: for his fake, they are plundred of their eſtates, and ſuffer the <hi>spoiling of their goods with joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.34.</note> perſwading <hi>themſelves that in heaven they have a better and more enduring ſubſtance:</hi> for Chriſt ſake they are reproached in their names, to this very hour, ſaith <hi>Paul, We hunger and thirst, and are naked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and are buffeted, and have no certain dwelling place,</hi> reviled, perſecuted, defamed, we <hi>are made the filth of the world</hi> and the off-ſcowring, of <hi>all things:</hi> For Chriſts ſake, in <hi>their bodies</hi> they are impriſoned as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas;</hi> baniſhed from their deareſt relations, driven from their ſweeteſt comforts: How were the Martyrs ſtoned,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.37, 38</note> 
               <hi>ſawn aſunder, ſtain</hi> with the <hi>Sword?</hi> How were they forced to wander in ſheep-skins, <hi>and goat-skins, in deſerts and in mountains,</hi> in dens and in <hi>the caves of the earth, deſtitute, afflicted, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented?</hi> and yet were they, in their generations, men more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113005:25"/>then the <hi>gold of Ophir,</hi> of whom the world <hi>was not worthy.</hi> And how did the modern Martyrs ſing in the flames, triumphing in Chriſt?<note place="margin">Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> for thy Name ſake <hi>are we ſlain all the day</hi> long, <hi>and we are counted as ſheep to the ſtaughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Resp. </seg>3</label> As their comforts are fewer, their diſcomforts heavier in this life, ſo that in regard of the things <hi>of this life, they are</hi> more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable: So conſider them in reference to the <hi>life to come,</hi> and you ſhall finde, that the great work of grace is to take up their ſpirits from this world,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14, 16.</note> to look <hi>for the bleſſed hope</hi> and glorious <hi>appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the great God.</hi> Hence it is that,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1.Firſt, Their <hi>apprehenſions of heaven are larger;</hi> Chriſt hath taken up their ſouls unto the tops of <hi>Piſga,</hi> and hath <hi>diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to them the land of Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> and hath given them more then others to taſte the powers of <hi>the world to come,</hi> and to ſit with <hi>him in heavenly places,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hen. 6.4. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.6. 1 Cor. 13 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and though they ſee but little, and that little darkly, as in a <hi>glaſſe,</hi> whilſt they are in their way, to what they ſhall ſee, when they are in their Countrey, when <hi>they ſhall ſee God face to face, and know him, as they are known of him;</hi> yet they ſee ſo much, as they cannot but admire, O how <hi>great is thy goodneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 31.19.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, which thou haſt laid up for them that fear thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Their <hi>affections towards heaven are ſtronger:</hi> Carnall hearts that know not God, believe not the things of Chriſt; though they be never <hi>ſatisfied</hi> with the <hi>earth,</hi> yet they are very <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> about the things of <hi>heaven:</hi> If I be ſaved, ſaith ſuch a wretch, I ſhall be ſaved; if I <hi>be damned,</hi> who <hi>can help it?</hi> I ſhall <hi>not be alone,</hi> I ſhall be as <hi>well as others,</hi> I will <hi>endure it as well as I can.</hi> What? endure the loſſe of heaven, endure the wrath of the Almighty God? oh poor wretch, when thy ſoul comes to ſee but a glimpſe,<note place="margin">Lu. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.28, 29.</note> what heaven is, and ſhalt ſee others coming from the Eaſt and Weſt, <hi>ſitting down with Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven, and thy ſelf ſhut out;</hi> when they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, thy ſoul to be excluded, this will cauſe <hi>weeping, and wailing and gnaſhing</hi> of teeth for ever.<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 8.</note> If <hi>Rachel</hi> could not <hi>endure the loſſe of her children.</hi> If <hi>Jacob</hi> could not endure the ſuppoſed loſſe of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 37.35.</note> and when all his <hi>ſons and daughters roſe up to comfort him, he refuſed to be comforted,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I will go down into the grave</hi> to my <hi>ſon mourning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 7.23.</note> If <hi>Ahithophel</hi> could not <hi>endure</hi> in the <hi>reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113005:25"/>of his counſell.</hi> If <hi>Mordecai could not endure the want of the</hi> bowing of the <hi>knee of Mordecai.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth 5.13.</note> If Queen <hi>Mary</hi> could not endure the loſſe of <hi>Callis,</hi> but ſaid when ſhe was dead, if they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened her they ſhould finde the loſſe of <hi>Callis written upon her heart:</hi> how then can thy ſoul endure the loſſe of eternity? The Saints know this and believe it, and the thoughts of the loſſe of heaven, cuts them to the heart; their ſouls are made willing to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe any <hi>loſſe on earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.24.</note> and they count not <hi>their lives dear unto themſelves,</hi> ſo they may finiſh their courſe with joy. But when they have willingly over gone the loſſe of all the comforts on the earth, of their eſtates, their liberties, their lives, then to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe the loſſe of heaven: this is that which they prayed againſt all their lives long, <hi>O draw me not away with the wicked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 28.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Not only their affections are thus ſet on <hi>things above,</hi> but <hi>their converſation is in heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> from whence they <hi>look for the Saviour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who ſhall <hi>change this vile body, that it may be like</hi> unto his glorious body: for this they both la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſuffer; this is that for which all the daies of their Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, ſince their converſion, they have been trading and traffick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for; now, when they have laid out <hi>all they are,</hi> and all <hi>they have</hi> for the purchaſing this pearl, if at the end of their life, they ſhould be deprived of this purchaſed poſſeſſion, this muſt needs make them more miſerable.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. The love that they bear to Jeſus Chriſt <hi>is ſweeter:</hi> Chriſt hath led them <hi>into his wine-cellar,</hi> and taken them up into the <hi>bed of love,</hi> eſpouſed <hi>them to himſelf,</hi> and <hi>kiſſed them with the kiſſes of his mouth,</hi> when others are meer ſtrangers to theſe ſpirituall em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces: what if a ſtranger count it no miſery to be ſevered from Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſa. 54.6.</note> yet what woman is not <hi>grieved in ſpirit</hi> for the <hi>loſſe of the husband of her youth?</hi> What ſaies a poor Chriſtian, muſt Chriſt and <hi>my ſoul part</hi> now? God forbid. The time was I did not <hi>know</hi> him, nor long <hi>after</hi> him, when the thoughts of Chriſt were not in my heart, then to have been ſevered from Chriſt would have appeared to me to have been no great miſery;<note place="margin">Gal. 4.9.</note> but now when my ſoul hath <hi>known</hi> him, or rather <hi>is known of him,</hi> when the deſires <hi>of my ſoul have been</hi> let out towards Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.</note> 
               <hi>and the remembrance of his name;</hi> when I have made Chriſt <hi>my joy,</hi> my <hi>crown of rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> now to part with that, which my ſoul loves, will <hi>make me
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113005:26"/>miſerable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth 1.16.</note> therefore the poor ſoul cleaves to Chriſt, as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Intreat me not to leave thee nor forſake thee,</hi> where ever thou goeſt let me goe, that where thou art, there my ſoul may be alſo.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. Conſider that the <hi>expectations of the Saints</hi> are <hi>firmer.</hi> It is the hope of heaven, that makes them paſſe <hi>thorow good report and bad report,</hi> the gladneſſe of their hearts is not the <hi>joy of ſenſe,</hi> but the rejoycing <hi>in the hope of the glory of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and this hope holds them above all fears, to this hope they flee, as to a <hi>Rock of refuge,</hi> ſet before them: and for this cauſe they faint not, and all <hi>theſe light afflictions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b 11.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>which are but for a moment,</hi> they count un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be <hi>compared to the glory which ſhall be revealed</hi> to them, willing they are to count <hi>themſelves Pilgrims and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers upon earth, ſeeking this heavenly</hi> Countrey, this houſe not made with hands, this <hi>inheritance immortall, undefiled and that never fades away.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet 1.4.</note> They that were never born to theſe <hi>high hopes,</hi> may better bear their mean condition: but after the abundant mercy of God hath begotten <hi>them again to this lively hope,</hi> and raiſed them up to all theſe glorious expectances,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.3.</note> then to goe diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, muſt needs make them <hi>miſerable.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 6 12, 20.</note> If the Troops of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> when they looked, and the <hi>companies of Sheba when they waited</hi> for waters, and found none: if they were <hi>confounded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had hoped:</hi> if the ſons of Nobles, in that time of drought returned <hi>aſhamed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>confounded,</hi> and <hi>with their heads co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,</hi> becauſe they came to the pits <hi>and found no waters:</hi> if in petty expectations here below,<note place="margin">Iſa 9 11.</note> we often times <hi>roar like Bears,</hi> and <hi>mourn ſore like Doves,</hi> when we look for judgement, but there is <hi>none, and for ſalvation,</hi> but it is farre from us: what ſoul can then bear the diſappointments of eternity? But ſurely <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of Chriſt <hi>works hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.4. verſ. 5.</note> and this hope will never make the ſoul of any Chriſtian <hi>to be aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Adde to all the former, not only the diſappointment of their hope, but <hi>the disparagement of Chriſt their head,</hi> whoſe name is more tender to their ſouls then the apple of their eye. Where is the great work of Chriſts redemption? from what evils did Chriſt redeem his people from? If his people have onely hope in Chriſt for this life, ſurely from the evils of this life the beſt of the Saints are not <hi>exempted,</hi> to the greateſt of theſe evils they <hi>lie expoſed;</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113005:26"/>where, and what then is the inheritance of the Saints in light? where are thoſe ſons and daughters that the Captain of ſalvation made perfect through ſufferings, <hi>bringeth unto glory?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.10.</note> What are become of all thoſe precious promiſes of Jeſus Chriſt?<note place="margin">Joh. 14.2.</note> I goe to <hi>prepare a place for you;</hi> In my Fathers houſe there are many man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: What is become of all the prayers and <hi>ſtrong cries</hi> that Chriſt uttered in the daies of his fleſh? Father I will, that <hi>thoſe that thou hast given me were with me where I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17.24.</note> that they may behold <hi>my glory.</hi> Surely, if the hope of the Saints be limited to this life, then Chriſt is diſparaged, and all the expectation of the Saints diſappointed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It may be this Doctrine is true for thoſe Chriſtians that are poor, that live in a low, afflicted condition, whoſe <hi>ſorrows</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> doe abound, whoſe life is made bitter unto them by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſore bondage: but what doe you ſay to great men, whoſe <hi>cup</hi> is full and runs over, upon <hi>whoſe tabernucle</hi> the <hi>Almighty ſhineth?</hi> in this life God hath made their <hi>portion very fat,</hi> and their <hi>meat to be plenteous;</hi> and if there be no other life beſide this, ſure of all men, in this life, they are moſt happy, and in what ſenſe can it be ſaid, in life or death, upon this ſuppoſall, that of all men they are moſt miſerable?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> The text ſpeaks of Chriſtians that are <hi>good,</hi> rather then <hi>of them</hi> that are <hi>great;</hi> and if God hath made men both great and good,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119 96.</note> and hath called your ſouls into fellowſhip with Chriſt: he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened your eyes to <hi>ſee an end</hi> of all theſe ſeeming <hi>perfections</hi> before you come to your end; and then what is all the greatneſſe upon earth, in compariſon to one daies communion with the great God? Beſides, the more <hi>you</hi> enjoy in your life, the more you are <hi>to loſe and leave at your</hi> death; and is it not a miſery in death to be ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of all? if beggars ſo unwillingly put off their raggs, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing are Princes to be plucked away from their robes, and the ſons of Nobles to goe down into the grave, and there to make their bed in the darke? what greater <hi>unhappineſſe</hi> is there, then to ſay, <hi>I have been happy,</hi> but now I muſt be plundred of all, and be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in an <hi>undone condition,</hi> never to take pleaſure any more, and there is nothing of honour, nor of all my labour <hi>wherein I have ſhewed my ſelf wiſe</hi> under the Sun, <hi>that I may take</hi> away with me in my hand? This <hi>is a ſore</hi> evil, that in <hi>all points, as I came naked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5 16.</note>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:113005:27"/>ſo I <hi>must goe;</hi> where the riſe is <hi>highest,</hi> the downfall is greateſt, and there is no down-fall like that of great <hi>Babel,</hi> How art thou <hi>fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, ſonne of the</hi> morning? Hell <hi>from beneath is moved</hi> for thee,<note place="margin">Iſa. 14.11, 12.</note> to meet <hi>thee at thy</hi> coming, thy pomp is <hi>brought down to the grave,</hi> and the noiſe of thy viols, the worme is ſpread under thee, and the worms cover thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> I have not time to ſhew the ſad condition of them that are without hope, that walk <hi>by ſight</hi> and not <hi>by faith,</hi> that as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall will have their portion in their own hands,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.14.</note> and in this life have their <hi>conſolation:</hi> what will theſe poor ſouls doe, when all their water in <hi>the bottle is spent,</hi> and their lives draw near to death, and their daies to the deſtroyers? there are others alſo, whoſe condition is yet more dreadfull, that not only <hi>neglect</hi> this hope in themſelves,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3 4.</note> but <hi>deride</hi> it in others, that walk after their own luſt, ſaying, where is <hi>the promiſe of his coming?</hi> who are a generation of men, that need rather to be lamented, then to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed; they ſhame the counſell of <hi>the poor, becauſe he makes the Lord his hope.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Only let me intreat you to enquire ſtrictly, whether Chriſt hath wrought this hope in you; the times wherein we live are gloomy daies, we may be ſuddenly, we muſt be ſhortly call'd out to a fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie triall; let not then our evidences be to ſeek, when they ſhould be uſed: this leaſe is expiring, and if there be no poſſibility to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new it,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> it is time to provide elſewhere for ſome certainty: it is our duty to <hi>make our calling and election ſure,</hi> and bleſſed be God that there is a poſſibility for the main to be aſſured, when all other things are endangered: You are <hi>bound to give a reaſon of the hope that is in you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>with meekneſſe and with fear:</hi> and if you owe this duty unto others, you owe it much more unto your own ſouls; if you dare not ſeriouſly commune with your own hearts in the day of peace, what ſhall you doe in the day of trouble, and in the <hi>ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of Jordan?</hi> If any ask, may this hope be diſcerned? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, though this hope in ſome be <hi>reall</hi> and <hi>radicall,</hi> where it is not <hi>viſible,</hi> yet it is poſſible to be <hi>diſcerned</hi> where it is, and <hi>need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> to be <hi>attained</hi> where it is not.</p>
            <p>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe Exam.</label> For the <hi>diſcovery</hi> of it where it is, it is very helpfull to conſider, 1. The <hi>Cauſes</hi> that <hi>breed it.</hi> 2. The <hi>graces that</hi> doe <hi>accompany</hi> it: and, 3. The effects that <hi>follow</hi> it. I may not preſume to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113005:27"/>handle the two former, give me leave to inſiſt upon the latter; Conſider the effects of hope in a four-fold demeanour of the ſoul towards <hi>hope it ſelf, towards God the authour</hi> and <hi>object</hi> of it, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the world, or the Word of God, the ground of hope.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Signe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, The carriage of the ſoul towards hope it ſelf,<note place="margin">The effect of hope in the carriage of the ſoul towards hope. Pſal. 17.14.</note> appears in theſe or ſuch particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the ſoul that hath this <hi>hope in heaven would by no means confine this hope to earth,</hi> but praies with the Pſalmiſt, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me from the <hi>wicked, from the men of this world, that have their portion in this life:</hi> When Chriſt diſcovered the ſad condition of the Phariſees, he ſaid, Woe unto them, verily I ſay unto you, <hi>you have your reward:</hi> why, might they ſay,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.2.</note> if we have it we are the ſurer of it, and a little in hand is better then much in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But what ever you imagine, this is certain, there can be no greater miſery, then to have your reward in this life, where you have but a <hi>ſhort being;</hi> and to have no reward in another, where you are to have your <hi>everlaſting being,</hi> therefore Chriſt denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth their condition to be woefull,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.24.</note> that in this life have <hi>received their conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. The Saints would not <hi>exchange their hopes</hi> of heaven, for the poſſeſſion of all the good things on earth: it was a bold ſpeech of <hi>Paul</hi> to King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> I would to God that <hi>not only thou,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 26.29.</note> 
               <hi>but that all that hear me, were not almoſt, but altogether ſuch as I am:</hi> Why <hi>Paul,</hi> what is thy condition, that thou deſireſt not to be like to King <hi>Agrippa,</hi> but the King to be like to thee, and not almoſt, but altogether? ſurely <hi>Pauls</hi> happineſſe was not in <hi>hand,</hi> but in <hi>hope,</hi> conſiſting in this, <hi>I know whom I have believed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.12.</note> nay ſuch high thoughts have the Saints of this hope, that take the pooreſt ſoul, that hath many doubts, and fears, and temptations and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that never attained any certainty of hope: ask that ſoul, wilt thou part with a poſſibility of heaven? why doſt thou <hi>wait any longer?</hi> that ſoul for all the world would not part with a <hi>poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of heaven</hi> in <hi>reverſion,</hi> to obtain the whole earth <hi>in preſent poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion;</hi> whereas the carnall heart and groundleſly confident, will eaſily part with his ſeeming certainty of heaven,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.16.</note> for the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of <hi>earth,</hi> and is as profane <hi>Eſau,</hi> who <hi>ſold his birth-right for a moſſe of pottage;</hi> but the Saints prize unſpeakably more a meer poſſibility, then a carnall heart doth all his ſeeming <hi>certainty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:113005:28"/>
            <p>Thirdly, The ſoule ſo prizeth this hope, that it is <hi>never content</hi> without it, full of doubts, unwilling to be deceived, unable to be held in ſuſpenſe, inquiſitive into his owne condition, giving all <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligente to attaine the full aſſurance of hope to the end,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.11.</note> this is the griefe that poor Saints mourne under, the great weight that they cannot beare, crying out as the Church ſaith, I ſeek him <hi>whom my ſoule loveth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17.</note> 
               <hi>I ſeek him but I finde him not:</hi> but ſtill enquiring, Oh tell me where thou lodgeſt, thou whom my ſoule loveth; and I charge you,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>Oh ye daughters of Jeruſalem,</hi> it you meet him whom my ſoule loves, tell him that I am <hi>ſick of love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, The Saints ſo prize this hope, that when <hi>it is attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> they count this hope <hi>their cheife contentment.</hi> The joy of the Saints conſiſts in holding faſt the <hi>confidence and rejoycing of their hope ſure unto the end;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.6.</note> well may the Pſalmiſt ſay, <hi>My lines are fallen in a good place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.5.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord is the portion of my cup.</hi> When the ſeventy Diſciples returned with joy, telling Chriſt, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils are <hi>ſubject unto us</hi> through thy name,<note place="margin">Luk 10.17. ver. 20.</note> Chriſt anſwers, <hi>In this rejoyce not, that the ſpirits are ſubject unto you:</hi> what, not joy in this? to heale all diſeaſes, to caſt out Devils: if this be not a cauſe of joy, what is? or what can be? Chriſt anſwers, rejoyce in this rather, <hi>that your names are written in the book of life;</hi> this hope made <hi>Paul</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>I have learned in every eſtate therewith to be content,</hi> and hath made all Saints in all ages to be confident, <hi>that godlines is profitable for all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8, Job 21.14.</note> whereas carnall men have undervalued the wayes of God, and have been ever queſtioning, what profit <hi>ſhall we have if we pray unto him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, When this hope is attained, the ſoule <hi>will not adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the loſſe of it, for the attainment of the best things in the Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>but counts all things as loſſe and dung, in respect of this; chuſing rather to ſuffer afflictions with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> 
               <hi>that are but for a moment;</hi> and liking this choice ſo well, that no arguments can draw them from it;<note place="margin">Joh. 6.68.</note> whither <hi>ſhould we goe? Lord thou hast the words of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life;</hi> no nor will the Saints adventure this hope, <hi>for the avoiding of the worſt condition,</hi> for this hopes ſake they have bin<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 5.41.</note> 
               <hi>impriſoned,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 10.33.</note> 
               <hi>plundered,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 11.37.</note> 
               <hi>baniſhed,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 11.35.</note> 
               <hi>tormented,</hi> and all too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; hope cauſing them to triumph, that all theſe light afflictions, <hi>which are but for a moment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>worke unto them a more exceeding weight of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:113005:28"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Effect. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Conſider the carriage of the ſoule, that hath this hope towards God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, The ſoule that hath this hope, <hi>adoreth the riches of gods love,</hi> that man may come to God <hi>in the new and living way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> when <hi>Adam</hi> fled from God, and the damned ſpirits cannot indure the approaches of Chriſt, but cry out, <hi>What have we to doe with thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 9.29. Ezra 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>thou Jeſus of Nazareth, that yet there is hope in the God of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> for ſuch ſinnes as they have committed, and for ſuch ſinners as they confeſſe themſelves to be: when all other hopes faile; that there is yet <hi>hopes of Heaven</hi> to poore ſinners that are conſcious of <hi>their deſerts of Hell:</hi> here are the exceeding riches of his glory, and that height and depth, and ſuch dimenſions of love, that the more they <hi>know the love</hi> of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.19.</note> the more they finde <hi>t paſſeth knowledge,</hi> and their apprehenſions of this love end in admirations: <hi>behold what manner of love the father had bestowed upon us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.1.</note> that we ſhould be called the <hi>ſonnes of God, who are the children of wrath</hi> by nature?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, This hope as it admireth the love of God to us, ſo it <hi>inlargeth the ſoule in love to God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>for the love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth us,</hi> if Chriſt died, <hi>then were we all dead, and therefore we that live, are no longer to live to our ſelves,</hi> to our own eaſe, and carnall contentment, but to the praiſe of him who love us, and gave himſelfe for us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, This hope <hi>maketh us to eye God,</hi> to ſee him that is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible,</hi> to ſet God at <hi>our right hand,</hi> to make his glory our end,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.27. Pſal. 16.8. Pſal. 25.15. Rom. 8.24.</note> and our aime: <hi>our eyes are ever to the Lord, and he ſhall bring us out of our diſtreſſe;</hi> this keepeth the ſoule in a <hi>waiting conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and not to be <hi>weary</hi> in looking upward.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, This hope <hi>transformeth us into Gods nature:</hi> he that hath this hope in him, <hi>purifieth himſelf even as God is pure;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.1.</note> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on every act of ſin, as an act of uncleannes; never counteth himſelfe pure enough; but while he is living, that ſoule is cleanſing himſelfe, till the ſoule come to be preſented to <hi>the father without ſpot or wrinkle.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, This hope <hi>ſweetens the thoughts of God and of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> maketh all thoſe glorious truths, as the day of the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that in their nature are very <hi>dreadfull,</hi> to grow <hi>delightfull,</hi> and ſetteth them into a ſtate of <hi>looking for,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113005:29"/>to the comming of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, This hope <hi>admireth the happineſſe of all that are in Chriſt,</hi> crying out,<note place="margin">Pſal. 65.4. Col. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chooſeſt,</hi> giving thanks that God hath counted any of the ſonnes of men <hi>meet to be partakers of the inheritance with the Saints in light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.18.</note> and beggeth for others, that their eyes may be opened to ſee <hi>what is the hope of this calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Effect. </seg>3</label> The third effect of this hope, appeareth in its demeanour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this world. The hope of Heaven,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Weakens our esteem</hi> of things below, enabling the ſoul to count it a ſmall thing <hi>to be judged in mans day;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3.</note> when we are riſen with Chriſt, then we begin to ſet our affections <hi>on things above,</hi> and not <hi>an things below.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>This leſſens our expectation from things below,</hi> ſheweth as the vanity of all earthly comforts, in their nature, in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, in their uſe,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.15.</note> that <hi>mans life doth not conſiſt in the abundance of theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, This hope keepeth <hi>the ſoule from ſwelling,</hi> when out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward comforts doe abound,<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.10.</note> 
               <hi>if riches increaſe, ſet not your hearts on them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, This hope <hi>preſerveth the ſoule from ſinking,</hi> when diſcomforts flow in to overwhelme it; calleth upon the ſoule, <hi>why art thou diſquieted in me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.5.</note> hope <hi>thou in God:</hi> there is more good to be received by hope, then we <hi>have lost,</hi> then we <hi>can loſe:</hi> that hope that bringeth the ſoule to the good <hi>that is eternall,</hi> onely can ſuſtaine the ſoule from ſinking under <hi>evil temporall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Effect. </seg>4</label> The fourth Effect of this hope is in its carriage towards the word of God: as hope holdeth up the <hi>ſoule from ſinking,</hi> ſo the word of God holdeth up <hi>faith from fainting;</hi> therefore all the children of hope are much affected with the word,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.49.</note> upon which God <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his ſervants to put their truſt:</hi> ſee what high expreſſions there are uſed in <hi>one Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> by him that was a <hi>man after Gods own heart.</hi> Firſt, is your eſteem of the word, ſuch as you can ſay with him in truth,<note place="margin">ver. 32. ver. 6. ver. 27. ver. 52.</note> 
               <hi>the Law of thy mouth is better then thouſands of Gold and Silver:</hi> and that you have <hi>reſpect unto all Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements:</hi> thy teſtimonies are my <hi>delight, and my counſellours:</hi> and thy ſtatutes <hi>have been my ſong, in the houſe of my Pilgrimage?</hi> Secondly, That your ſoules love this word, and can ſay, <hi>I love thy commandements above Gold, yea above much fine Gold: and how
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113005:29"/>ſweet is thy Word unto my taste? yea ſweeter then the honey,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 127. ver. 103. ver. 11. ver. 148. ver. 111. ver. 161.</note> 
               <hi>and the heney-combe.</hi> Thirdly, Are your deſires ſo after this word, that you <hi>hide it in your hearts,</hi> make it your <hi>meditation, claime it as your inheritance for ever: that your heart standeth in awe of his Word,</hi> that you have <hi>choſen the way of his precepts:</hi> that your ſoules can no more ſubſiſt <hi>without the Word</hi> of God, then your bodyes <hi>without food,</hi> and therefore your ſoule breaketh <hi>for the longing it hath to Gods precept at all times:</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 20. 1 Pet. 2.2. Job. 23.12.</note> 
               <hi>that you deſire the word as new borne babes</hi> the breſts, and long for it, <hi>as much as for your appointed food?</hi> this is a ſtrong argument, your hope is grounded upon the Word of God, when the word <hi>doth nouriſt it:</hi> this word weakneth the hope of Hypocrites, diſcovereth the rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tennes of their vain confidence; but tis otherwiſe with the Saints, though their ſoules have many doubts, when they conſult with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reaſon, yet when they come <hi>to the law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 57.19.</note> 
               <hi>and to the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> the Lord createth <hi>the fruit of the lips to be peace,</hi> and when their <hi>light is cleereſt</hi> their hope <hi>is strongeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Let this Doctrine make your ſoules in love with this hope, which will be an <hi>arke</hi> to preſerve you when others are drowned, a <hi>City of refuge</hi> to ſecure you, when others fall into the hand of that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger of blood that doth purſue them: If any aske, how ſhall we attaine this frame of ſpirit, to ſet our hopes on God? I anſwer, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> Take theſe directions: Firſt, ſtrive to <hi>apprehend and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> upon the great bleſſing of Jeſus Chriſt; let the thoughts of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity dwell upon your hearts; things not <hi>apprehended</hi> can never be <hi>deſired,</hi> nor really <hi>expected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That you may apprehend theſe riches of Chriſts glory, <hi>beleeve the excellencies revealed</hi> in the Goſpel the object of hope is things inviſible, and faith muſt be the <hi>ground of ſuch things hoped for,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> and the onely <hi>evidence we can have for thoſe things that are not ſeen:</hi> if any prophane perſon reſolve, I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that there is a <hi>Heaven</hi> or a <hi>Hell,</hi> nor the powers of the world to come, till I ſee them; Conſider (poore ſoule) when theſe truths are the object of thy <hi>ſight,</hi> they cannot be the object of thy <hi>hope,</hi> for <hi>hope that is ſeen is not hope,</hi> for what a man ſeeth,<note place="margin">Rom. 8 24.</note> 
               <hi>why doth he yet hope for?</hi> beleeve therefore the excellencies of Jeſus Chriſt, otherwiſe thou wilt never be at the paines to cleare <hi>thy intereſt</hi> in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113005:30"/>them, and if Heaven be not firſt made the object of thy <hi>hope,</hi> it can never be made the object of thy <hi>ſight: expectation</hi> muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede <hi>fruition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Love the excellencies</hi> of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: many things may be beleeved as <hi>true,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fides eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum rerum &amp; bonarum, quare bona cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la: &amp; boc fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de bonà non malâ, &amp;c. <hi>Lombard.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> diſt. <hi>27. Pſal. 43, 4. Cant. 8.6.</hi>
               </note> and yet not loved as <hi>good: faith may be good, when the object of it is evil,</hi> for we are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve every truth which God revealeth, the evil of ſin, as truly as the goodneſſe of grace: but nothing is the object of hope, but what the ſoule is really perſwaded is <hi>truly good:</hi> where <hi>love</hi> is weake, the <hi>mind</hi> is careleſſe, and hope cannot be <hi>ſtrong:</hi> and that which is not earneſtly deſired, is never greedily expected: but when the deſires of our ſoule are earneſtly carryed out after Chriſt, when we ſet up Chriſt in our hearts as the <hi>gladnes of our joy,</hi> then we begin to long after him, then love and hope prove <hi>ſtrong as death, and hope deferred maketh the heart ſick:</hi> but this is the great privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this hope, though in all other things you may meet with diſappointments, yet God will fulfill <hi>the deſires of them that feare him,</hi> and the expectation of poore ſoules in Chriſt <hi>ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver goe away aſhamed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 13.12.</note> and when this hope is granted, it will be <hi>a tree of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, In the uſe of all meanes that God hath <hi>appointed,</hi> beg importunately <hi>the ſpirit of grace</hi> which God hath <hi>promiſed freely;</hi> tis beyond the ability of mans will, above the ſtrength of ordinances, above the reach of any created power, to worke this hope: <hi>tis eaſy to preſume,</hi> but to beleeve and hope in God <hi>that raiſeth up the dead,</hi> is an act of <hi>tranſcendent difficultie,</hi> for a poore ſoule under the ſenſe of ſinne, and Gods wrath, and ſight of Hell, to roll it ſelfe upon the rich mercy of Chriſt, to have all this guilt ſo great to be <hi>pardoned,</hi> and all the luſts that are ſtrong to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, this is onely <hi>the gift of God:</hi> and therefore pray that the eyes of <hi>your underſtanding may be opened,</hi> and that your hearts and conſciences may experimentally feele <hi>that exceeding working of his power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.19. 1 Pet. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead, that your faith and hope may be in God:</hi> and that your ſoules may be ſo in love with Heaven, and your perſwaſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo well grounded, that you may be above the <hi>love of this life,</hi> and above the <hi>feare of death,</hi> and that all the dayes of your <hi>appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>you may be waiting till your change come.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
